<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./apps.xml">
<properties>
<title>Building Applications</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section name="How to Build Applications">
<subsection name="About This Document">
<p>
This document outlines one possible sequence of development steps that can be followed to create a
Struts application.  It is not intended as a complete description of each
referenced development activity.  More detailed documentation is available
elsewhere and is referenced by "(more...)" links where possible.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Caveats">
<ol>
<li>Requirements development and design are outside of the scope of this  document.</li>
<li>For help installing Struts, see the <a href="../userGuide/installation.html">Getting Started</a> chapter.</li>
<li>There are many other ways to approach Struts development and there are many
    other features available besides the ones discussed below. This document
    outlines only one way to get started.</li>
<li>This document focuses on form/data centric applications, but may also work with
    other types of applications.</li>
<li>This material was written for Struts 1.1 (beta 2) and now 1.2.2</li>
</ol>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Overview">
<ol>
<li>Implement data entry forms as JSP files.</li>
<li>Implement one or more <code>ActionForm</code> descendents to buffer data
    between JSPs and Actions.</li>
<li>Create an XML document that defines the validation rules for your
    application.</li>
<li>Implement one or more <code>Action</code> descendents to respond form
    submissions.</li>
<li>Create <code>struts-config.xml</code> to associate forms with
    actions.</li>
<li>Create or update <code>web.xml</code> to reference
    <code>ActionServlet</code>, taglibs used by Struts.</li>
<li>Parallel Tasks
<ol>
<li>Building</li>
<li>Unit Testing</li>
<li>Deployment</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Details">
<ol>
<li>Implement data entry forms as JSP files.
<ol>
<li>Use elements from the <code>html</code> taglib
    to define the form elements. <a href="../userGuide/struts-html.html">
    (more...)</a></li>
<li>Use <code>message</code> and other elements from the <code>bean</code>
    taglib to define the labels and other static text of the form. 
    <a href="../userGuide/struts-bean.html">(more...)</a>
<ol>
<li>Create and maintain a properties file of the text elements
    to be displayed. <a href="../userGuide/preface.html#0_6_Properties_Files_and_ResourceBundles">(more...) 
    </a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Use <code>property</code> attributes to link form fields to 
    <code>ActionForm</code> instance variables.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Implement one or more <code>ActionForm</code> descendents
    to buffer data between JSPs and Actions.
<ol>
<li>Create get/set pairs that correspond to the property names
    in your related JSP form. Example:
<pre>&lt;html:text property="city" /&gt;</pre>
    needs:
<pre>getCity() and setCity(String c)</pre>
</li>
<li>When needed, create a <code>reset</code> method
    that sets the fields of the <code>ActionForm</code> to their default values. Most ActionForms do not need to do this.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Create an XML document that defines the validation rules for your
    application.</li>
<li>Implement one or more <code>Action</code> descendents
    to respond to form submissions.
<ol>
<li>Descend from DispatchAction or LookupDispatchAction if you
    want one class to handle more than one kind of event (example: one Action
    to handle 'insert', 'update' and 'delete' events, using a different "surrogate" execute method for each). <a href="http://husted.com/struts/tips/002.html">(more...)</a></li>
<li>Use the <code>execute</code> method
    (or its surrogates) of your Action class to interface with objects in your
    application responsible for database interaction, such as EJBs, etc.
    <!-- [:TODO: find good doc to link to] -->
</li>
<li>Use the return value of the <code>execute</code> method
    (or its surrogates) direct the user interface to the appropriate next page.
<!-- [:TODO: find good doc to link to] -->
</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Create <code>struts-config.xml</code> to
    associate forms with actions. The file minimally needs:</li>
<li>Create or update <code>web.xml</code> to
    reference <code>ActionServlet</code>, taglibs used by Struts. <a href="../userGuide/configuration.html#5_4_The_Web_Application_Deployment_Descriptor"> (more...)</a></li>
<li>Parallel Tasks
<ol>
<li>Building
<ol>
<li>Use Ant. It can compile, create WAR file, perform XSLT
   transformations, run unit tests, interact with version control systems,
   clean up, etc. <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant"> (more...)</a></li>
<li>Create and use build script incrementally, as you create
    files that need to be copied, compiled, etc. </li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Unit Testing
<ol>
<li>Unit test normal java beans with JUnit. <a href="http://www.junit.org"> (more...)</a></li>
<li>Unit test JSP, taglibs and conventional servlet components
    with Cactus. <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/cactus"> (more...)</a></li>
<li>Unit test Action servlets with StrutsTestCase. <a href="http://strutstestcase.sourceforge.net"> (more...)</a></li>
<li>Add all unit tests to the build script as a separate
    target. This target should use the <code>junit</code> tag to launch each TestCase descendent. <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant/manual/OptionalTasks/junit.html"> (more...)</a></li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Deployment
<ol>
<li>Build script should create a war file containing the
    files developed above, along with files that make up the Struts framework.
    <!-- [:TODO: describe this further, look for doc to link to] -->
</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol></subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
