<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./newbie.xml">
<properties>
<title>How Does Struts Work? - Apache Struts</title>
</properties>
<body>
<section href="faq" name="How does Struts work?">

<subsection href="how" name="How does Struts work?">

<p>
    Java Servlets are designed to handle requests made by Web browsers.
    Java ServerPages are designed to create dynamic Web pages that can turn billboard sites into live applications.
    Struts uses a special Servlet as a switchboard to route requests from Web browsers to the appropriate ServerPage.
    This makes Web applications much easier to design, create, and maintain.
</p>

<p>
    Here is some more detail on the mechanisms and dependencies of Struts:
</p>

<ul>
   <li>
      The web application that you develop has a deployment descriptor
      (<code>WEB-INF/web.xml</code>) which you must write. This file describes
      the configuration of your web application, including welcome pages (the
      file that is shown in a directory when none is specified by the request),
      mappings to servlets (path or extension name), and parameters to those
      servlets.<br/>

      In this file, you configure the Struts
      <a href="../api/org/apache/struts/action/ActionServlet.html"><code>ActionServlet</code></a>
      as the servlet that will handle all requests for a given mapping (usually
      the extension <code>.do</code>). This is the "switchboard" mentioned
      above.<br/>

      In this same file, you configure the <code>ActionServlet</code> to use
      one or more configuration files for Struts itself.<br/>
      For this text, assume we are installing the web application on the server
      at <code>/myapp</code>, and are using the simplest possible configuration
      from there.<br/>

      If you need more details on deployment descriptors, read
      the Servlet Specification available from Sun Microsystem's
      <a href="http://java.sun.com">Java site</a>.<br/>
   </li>
   <li>
      In the Struts configuration file(s), you associate paths with
      the controller components of your application, known as
      <a href="../api/org/apache/struts/action/Action.html"><code>Action</code></a>
      classes (i.e. "login" ==&gt; LoginAction class). This tells the Struts
      <code>ActionServlet</code> that when the incoming request is
      <code>http://myhost/myapp/login.do</code> it should invoke your
      controller component <code>LoginAction</code>.<br/>

      Note the extension <code>.do</code> in this URL. The extension causes
      your container (i.e.  Tomcat) to call the <code>ActionServlet</code>,
      which sees the word "login" as the thing you want to do. The
      configuration is referenced, and your <code>LoginAction</code> is
      executed.<br/>
   </li>
   <li>
      For each <code>Action</code>, you also configure Struts with the names of
      the resulting page(s) that can be shown as a result of that action. There
      can be more than one view as the result of an action (often, there are at
      least two: one for success, and one for failure).<br/>

      Your <code>Action</code> (the controller component you write) is based on
      these <em>logical</em> result mapping names. It reports back to the
      <code>ActionServlet</code> using words like "success", "failure",
      "ready", "ok", "UserIsIncompetent", etc.  The Struts system (through the
      configuration that you wrote) knows how to forward to the proper
      <em>specific</em> page. This has the added advantage of reconfiguration of
      the view layer by simply editing the Struts XML configuration file.<br/>

      At this point Struts knows how to delegate to your controller components,
      and what to show as a result of your controller processing. The "model"
      part of the application is completely up to you, and is called from
      within your controller components.
   </li>
   <li>
      You may also associate a Java Bean with an action (or set of actions) in
      the Struts configuration file. The Java Bean is used as a repository for
      form or display data that can be communicated between the view and
      controller layer.<br/>

      These Beans are automatically made visible to your controller components
      (like <code>LoginAction</code>) and any view page that is associated with
      that controller. <br/>

      These Beans can also be validated with the help of the Struts system to
      help insure that the user is putting good data in the form. They can be
      carried along with a session, allowing forms to span multiple pages of
      the view, and Actions in the controller.<br/>

      <strong>Note</strong>: You must be using some sort of server-side
      technology (JSP, Velocity, XSLT) for the view layer (going <em>to</em> the
      client) to see this data (plain HTML won't work). Struts works on the
      server side, so the client's view has to be composed there.<br/>

      The client feeds the data back through normal form submission (POST/GET)
      methods, and the Struts system updates that data in the Bean before
      calling your controller components.
   </li>
   <li>
      Within your web application will be pages that represent the view your
      users will see. These can be JSP pages, Velocity Templates,
      XSLT pages, and so forth.
      A set of JSP tags is bunded with the Struts distribution so that you
      can get started right away, but any standard presentation technology
      can be used with Struts.<br/>

      Even plain HTML files can be used within your Struts application,
      although they will not take full advantage of all of the dynamic
      features.<br/>

      Following the example of the Struts JSP taglibs, several other
      packages are available to make the framework easy to use with your
      favorite presentation technology.
      For Velocity templates, there are the
      <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">Velocity</a> ViewTools
      for Struts.
      If you want to use XSLT in you application, you can choose between
      <a href="http://www.openroad.ca/opencode/">stxx</a> and
      <a href="http://it.cappuccinonet.com/strutscx/">
      StrutsCX</a>.<br/>

      These packages make the standard Struts framework elements look and
      feel like a seamless part of the original presentation technology.
      Struts also makes it easy to mix and match.
      If need be, you can use JSP, Velocity templates, and XSLT all in
      the same application!<br/>

      Since Struts relies on standard Servlet technologies, you should be
      able to use any Java presentation technology with Struts.
   </li>
   <li>
      While the focus of the Struts framework is on the controller,
      the presentation layer is a significant part of any application.
      The Struts JSP taglibs include a number of generic and Struts-specific
      tags to help you use dynamic data in your view. <br/>

      The custom JSP tags account for a good deal of the Struts code base. It
      is educational to note that as of version 1.1b3 the Java code for the
      core of Struts was about 28,000 lines, and the Java code for the tag
      libraries (including tiles) was about 41,000 lines.<br/>

      These tags help you glue your view layer to the controller layer without
      having to embed a lot of Java in the JSP. This gives the page an XML
      look, and can be easier for web designers to deal with than a plain JSP. It
      also helps minimize dependencies between the controller and view.<br/>

      The custom tags are used to create forms (and invisibly interact with the
      Bean mentioned previously), logically forward to other pages, and invoke
      other actions of the web application.<br/>

      There are also tags that help you with internationalization, error
      messages, etc.<br/>

      All of these abilities depend in some way on the configuration files you
      supplied to Struts.
   </li>
</ul>
<p>
   It is important for you to remember that the mechanism described here is
   only in effect when the <code>ActionServlet</code> is handling the
   request.
</p>
<p>
   Since this only happens when a request is submitted that causes your
   container (i.e. Tomcat, WebSphere, etc.) to call <code>ActionServlet</code>,
   you must be sure that any page that relies on Struts is done through a
   request that will map to the <code>ActionServlet</code> (i.e. has a
   <code>.do</code> extension).
</p>
 </subsection>

</section></body></document>
