<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="index.html">

  <properties>
    <title>Shale Framework</title>
  </properties>

  <body>


    <section name="Shale Framework"      href="background">


      <subsection name="Background"      href="background-background">

        <p>Little did anyone know, when the first few lines of code were
        committed to the <a href="http://struts.apache.org">Struts</a>
        CVS repository in June 2000, that a revolution was brewing.  Prior
        to that time, there were few useful models for best practices for
        the architecture of web based applcations.  The best we could do
        was handwaving about "Model 1" and "Model 2" approaches.</p>

        <p>The original implementation of Struts, which was released as a
        1.0 product approximately one year later, changed all that.  As
        more and more people came to understand the advantages of building
        on top of a stable and supported framework, and as more and more
        developers adopted it for their own application development, and
        as more and more books helped everyone understand how to use the
        framework correctly, and as more and more development tools provided
        support for building Struts based applications, the word changed.
        A small open source project became a defacto industry standard that,
        even today, is very popular.</p>

        <p>But that was then ... and this is now.  In the years that Struts
        has been around (five and counting as of this writing), vastly
        improved technologies have become available from many talented
        architects and designers.  Moore's Law has continued its seemingly
        inexhaustible progress.  Developers have grown in their ability to
        understand the benefits of a monolithic controller architecture ...
        as well as increasingly developing preferences towards agility,
        code reuse, unit tests, and building applications by composition
        instead of inheritance.</p>

        <p>One of the critical success factors for Struts has been, and
        continues to be, an obvious commitment on the part of the Struts
        developers towards backwards compatibility.  This has led to Struts
        being both praised (for protecting the investment of developers
        with thousands of applications critically dependent on the framework)
        and dissed (for being a dinosaur compared to all the "latest and
        greatest" favorite technological approaches).  History has shown,
        in terms of its continued popularity, that this is a good
        strategic approach.</p>

        <p>But, it is also time to harvest many of the great ideas that have
        matured in the last several years.  It is time to base a web tier
        framework on top of the new standard API in this space (JavaServer Faces),
        and eliminate the need to implement redundant features, instead of just
        treating JSF as a UI component technology.  It is time to answer the
        question "if we knew then what we know now, what would Struts have
        looked like?"</p>

        <p>Thus, Shale is a proposal for a modern web application framework,
        fundamentaly based on JavaServer Faces, and focused on improving
        ease of use for developers adopting JSF as a foundational technology
        in their own development environments.  At the same time, the
        architecture of Shale is a set of fine grained services (and service
        options) that can be combined as needed to meet particular application
        requirements, rather than a monolithic request processor that is hard
        to customize and extend.  In addition, integration links for other
        frameworks and framework components are provided, to ease development
        when combinations of technologies are required.</p>

        <blockquote><em>EDITOR'S NOTE:  Why "Shale"?  As others have pointed out,
        the cultural rules of engagement at Apache encourage both evolution
        and revolution in software designs.  Revolutions are typically assigned
        code names while they are under discussion, gaining access to the
        branding of the overall project once they are accepted (or, going off
        on their own if they are not).  Other proposals for Struts 2.x have
        talked about tearing down the walls inside the framework, and those
        are Good Things.  Shale's architecture, on the other hand, is based
        on the principle that we should fundamentally divide the notion of a
        web application framework into solid individual layers, much as we
        see geologically in shale deposits around our volcanoes and coastlines.
        Each layer of the framework should focus on the specific requirements
        that are relevant to that layer -- and use of one layer should not
        necessarily require the use of all the rest (although it's certainly
        reasonable for synergies to exist if all the layers are chosen :-).
        Hence, "shale".</em></blockquote>

      </subsection>


      <subsection name="Foundations"    href="background-foundations">

        <p>Shale is based on (and requires a runtime environment that
        supports) the following foundation technologies:</p>

        <ul>
        <li>Java Runtime Environment (JRE) 1.4 or later.</li>
        <li>Servlet API 2.4 or later. (*)</li>
        <li>JavaServer Pages 2.0 or later. (*)</li>
        <li>JavaServer Faces 1.1 or later.</li>
        <li>JSP Standard Tag Library (JSTL) 1.1 or later.</li>
        <li>Apache Commons BeanUtils 1.7 or later.</li>
        <li>Apache Commons Chain 1.0 or later.</li>
        <li>Apache Commons Digester 1.7 or later.</li>
        <li>Apache Commons Logging 1.0.4 or later.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>(*) Although the sample applications shipped with Shale are
        configured for these Servlet and JSP versions, at the time of this
        writing Shale itself does not rely on them; you can successfully
        run Shale based applications on a Servlet 2.3 / JSP 1.2 platform
        by using the appropriate syntax in deployment descriptors and JSP
        pages, and substituting a JSTL 1.0 library for the JSTL 1.1 library
        listed above.  This is <strong>not</strong> a committed feature for
        a 1.0 release, unless discussion on the development and user mailing
        lists indicates that it is important to a significant number of
        users.</p>

        <p>Various optional Shale components have dependencies on the following
        additional runtime technologies:</p>

        <ul>
        <li>Apache Commons Validator 1.1.4 or later.</li>
        <li>Spring Framework 1.2.2 or later.</li>
        <li>Struts Tiles (Stand Alone) - currently in Struts Sandbox.</li>
        </ul>

        <p>If you wish to work on Shale itself, you will require the following
        additional resources:</p>

        <ul>
        <li>Java Development Kit (JDK) 1.4 or later.</li>
        <li>Apache Ant 1.6.3 or later.</li>
        <li>FindBugs (SourceForge Project) 0.8.6 or later (optional).</li>
        <li>JUnit 3.8.1 or later.</li>
        </ul>
                
      </subsection>


    </section>


    <section name="Shale Features"       href="features">

      <p>The major features of the Shale Framework are described in the
      following detail sections:</p>

      <ul>
        <li><a href="features.html#view">View Controller</a> - Convenient
            mechanism to associate a "backing" Java class with each
            JavaServer Faces <em>view</em> in an application, with predefined
            event handers for events significant to an application developer.</li>
        <li><a href="features.html#dialog">Dialog Manager</a> - Mechanism to
            define a "conversation" with a user that requires multiple HTTP
            requests to implement, modeled as a state diagram.</li>
        <li><a href="features.html#application">Application Manager</a> -
            Traditional application wide front controller features that should
            be applied to every request.</li>
        <li><a href="features.html#validation">Validation</a> - Integration with
            the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/validator/">
            Jakarta Commons Validator Framework</a>, supporting both client side
            and server side validations based on a single set of configured
            validation rules.</li>
        <li><a href="features.html#remoting">Remoting</a> - Server side support
            for applications that employ <a href="http://wikipedia.org/wiki/AJAX">
            AJAX</a> (Asynchronous JavaScript and XML) style interactions.</li>
        <li><a href="features.html#spring">Spring Integration</a> - Integration
            with the <a href="http://www.springframework.org">Spring Framework</a>,
            allowing the use of Spring's dependency injection framework to create
            JavaServer Faces managed beans.</li>
        <li><a href="features.html#clay">Reusable Views</a> - An innovative
            sub-framework for supporting the configuration of reusable subtrees
            of JavaServer Faces components for customizable reuse.</li>
        <li><a href="features.html#test">Test Framework</a> - Set of mock objects
            and <a href="junit.org">JUnit</a> test case base classes suitable for
            testing both the framework classes themselves, as well as application
            components built on top of the framework.</li>
      </ul>

    </section>


    <section name="Shale Download"       href="download">

      <p>Nightly builds of Shale are available from
      <a href="http://cvs.apache.org/builds/struts/nightly/struts-shale/">
      http://cvs.apache.org/builds/struts/nightly/struts-shale/</a>.
      For convenience, there are four available packages:</p>

      <ul>
      <li><a href="http://cvs.apache.org/builds/struts/nightly/struts-shale/core-library/">
          Core Library</a> - The fundamental core of Shale, required for
          all applications using the framework.</li>
      <li><a href="http://cvs.apache.org/builds/struts/nightly/struts-shale/clay-plugin/">
          Clay Plug-In</a> - Library supporting reusable view fragments.</li>
      <li><a href="http://cvs.apache.org/builds/struts/nightly/struts-shale/test-framework/">
          Test Framework</a> - Library of mock objects and convenience base
          classes for JUnit test cases, suitable for testing both the framework
          itself and the components of applications built on top of Shale.</li>
      <li><a href="http://cvs.apache.org/builds/struts/nightly/struts-shale/use-cases/">
          Use Cases Sample App</a> - Composite set of use case based examples
          of Shale features.</li>
      </ul>

    </section>


    <section name="Shale Documentation"  href="documentation">

      <p>Online Javadocs for Shale (based on the SVN trunk) are
      periodically updated at:</p>

      <ul>
      <li><a href="http://people.apache.org/~craigmcc/shale-core-javadocs/">
          Core Library</a>.</li>
      <li><a href="http://people.apache.org/~craigmcc/shale-clay-javadocs/">
          Clay Plug-In</a>.</li>
      <li><a href="http://people.apache.org/~craigmcc/shale-test-javadocs/">
          Test Framework</a>.</li>
      <li><a href="http://people.apache.org/~craigmcc/shale-usecases-javadocs/">
          Use Cases Sample App</a>.</li>
      </ul>

    </section>


    <section name="Shale Issue Tracking" href="issue">

      <p>Please report any bugs, or log any enhancement requests, in the
      <a href="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla">Apache Issue Tracking System</a>,
      using product <code>Struts</code> and component <code>Shale</code>.</p>

    </section>


  </body>

</document>
