<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
Copyright 1999-2009 The Apache Software Foundation
Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<!--
// ======================================================================== 78
-->
<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Announcements</title>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Announcements">
            <p class="right">
                Skip to:
                <a href="announce-2012.html">Announcements - 2012</a>
            </p>

            <h4 id="a20130405">5 April 2013 - Apache Struts 1 End-Of-Life (EOL) Announcement</h4>
            <p>
                The Apache Struts Project Team would like to inform you that the Struts 1.x web framework has
                reached its end of life and is no longer officially supported.
            </p>
            <p>
                Please check the following readings to find more details.
                <ul>
                    <li><a href="struts1eol-announcement.html">Apache Struts 1 EOL Announcement</a>, including a detailed Q/A section</li>
                    <li><a href="struts1eol-press.html">Apache Struts 1 EOL Press Release</a></li>
                </ul>
            </p>

            <h4 id="a20130306">6 March 2013 - Struts 2.3.12 General Availability Release</h4>
            <p>
                The Apache Struts group is pleased to announce that Struts 2.3.12 is
                available as a "General Availability" release. The GA designation is our
                highest quality grade.
            </p>
            <p>
                Apache Struts 2 is an elegant, extensible framework for creating
                enterprise-ready Java web applications. The framework is designed to
                streamline the full development cycle, from building, to deploying, to
                maintaining applications over time.
            </p>
            <p>
                It's a mostly maintenance release but few important improvements were added as well:
                <ul>
                    <li>All validators were refactored and right now parameters can be set via OGNL also parameter parse was removed</li>
                    <li>Tag's required attribute was renamed to requiredLabel to allow support of Html5 required attribute in the tags</li>
                    <li>New Tiles 3 plugin was added to support Tiles 3 result type</li>
                    <li>Support for JBoss 5 to work with the Convention Plugin was improved</li>
                </ul>
                Please check the Version Notes to see more details.
            </p>
            <p>
                All developers are recommended to update existing Struts 2 applications to Struts 2.3.12.
            </p>
            <p>
                Struts 2.3.12 is available in a full distribution or as separate library, source, example and documentation
                distributions, from the
                <a href="http://struts.apache.org/download.cgi#struts2312">releases page</a>.
                The release is also available through the central Maven repository under Group ID "org.apache.struts". The
                <a href="http://struts.apache.org/development/2.x/docs/version-notes-2312.html">release notes</a>
                are available online.
            </p>
            <p>
                The 2.3.x series of the Apache Struts framework has a minimum
                requirement of the following specification versions: Servlet API 2.4,
                JSP API 2.0, and Java 5.
            </p>
            <p>
                Should any issues arise with your use of any version of the Struts
                framework, please post your comments to the user list, and, if
                appropriate, file a tracking ticket.
            </p>

        </section>
        <section>
            <p class="right">
                Skip to:
                <a href="announce-2012.html">Announcements - 2012</a>
            </p>

            <p class="right">
                <strong>Next:</strong>
                <a href="kickstart.html">Kickstart FAQ</a>
            </p>
        </section>

    </body>
</document>
