<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="preface.html">

  <properties>
    <title>The Struts User's Guide - Preface: Core Technologies</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="0. Preface: Core Technologies">

  <subsection name="0.1 The Usual Suspects" href="suspects">

    <p>
      This User Guide is written for active web developers and assumes a working
      knowledge about how Java web applications are built. Before getting started, you should
      understand the basics of several core technologies:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li><a href="#http">HTTP, HTML, and User Agents</a></li>
      <li><a href="#cycle">The HTTP Request/Response Cycle</a></li>
      <li><a href="#java">The Java Language and Application Frameworks</a></li>
      <li><a href="#javabeans">JavaBeans</a></li>
      <li><a href="#resources">Properties Files and  ResourceBundles</a></li>
      <li><a href="#servlets">Java Servlets</a></li>
      <li><a href="#jsp">JavaServer Pages and JSP Tag Libraries</a></li>
      <li><a href="#xml">Extensible Markup Language</a></li>
    </ul>

    <p>
    This chapter briefly defines each of these technologies but does not describe them in detail.
    For your convenience, links to further information are provided if you would like to learn more about a technology.
    </p>

    <p id="JavaWebServicesTutorial">If you are familiar with Java, but not these technologies,
    the best overall starting point is
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/index.html"><strong>The Java Web Services Tutorial</strong></a>.
    This document is also available for download in
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/JavaWSTutorial.pdf">PDF</a> format.
    </p>

    <p>If you've created web applications for other platforms, you may be able to follow along
    and visit the other references as needed. The core technologies used by Struts are
    also used by most other Java web development products, so the background information will be
    useful in any Java project.
    </p>

    <p id="jt">If you are not familiar with the Java language generally,
    then the best starting point is
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/index.html"><strong>The Java Tutorial</strong></a>.
    This overlaps with the Java Web Services Tutorial in some places, but the two work well together.
    </p>

      <p>
          For more about building Java application in general, see the
          <a href="http://developer.java.sun.com/developer/onlineTraining/new2java/divelog/part1/toc.jsp">New to
          Java Center</a>.
      </p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.2 HTTP, HTML and User Agents" href="http">

    <p>The World Wide Web was built over the Hypertext Transfer Protocol
    (<a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2616.txt?number=2616">HTTP</a>) and the Hypertext Markup Language
    (<a href="http://www.w3.org/MarkUp/">HTML</a>). A User Agent, like a web browser, uses HTTP to request
     a HTML document. The browser then formats and displays the document to its user. HTTP is used to
    transport more than HTML, but HTML is the lingua franca of the Web and web applications. </p>

    <p>While building web applications, some Java developers will write their own HTML. Others leave that responsibility to the
    page designers.</p>

    <p>For more about HTTP, HTML, and User Agents, see:</p>

    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://www.w3.org/MarkUp/Guide/"><strong>Getting started with HTML</strong></a> by Dave Raggett</li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/HTTP.html#63796">
    <strong>HTTP Overview</strong></a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial.</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2616.txt"><strong>HTTP/1.1
        </strong></a> Specification</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2617.txt"><strong>HTTP
        Basic and Digest Authentication</strong></a> Specification</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc2109.txt"><strong>State
        Management Mechanism</strong></a> Specification (Cookies)</li>
    </ul>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.3 The HTTP Request/Response cycle" href="cycle">

    <p>A very important part of HTTP for the web developer is the request/response cycle. To use HTTP
    you have to make a request. A HTTP server, like a web server, is then obliged to respond. When you
    build your web application, you design it to react to a HTTP request by returning a HTTP response.
    Frameworks like Struts abstract much of these nuts and bolts, but it is important to understand
    what is happening behind the scenes. </p>

    <p>If you are not familiar with the HTTP request/response cycle, we <strong>strongly</strong> recommend the
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/HTTP.html#63796">
    HTTP Overview</a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial.
    </p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.4 The Java Language and Application Frameworks" href="java">

    <p>Struts is written in the popular and versatile
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/jls/first_edition/html/index.html">Java programming language</a>.
    Java is an object-orientated language, and Struts makes good use of many
    object-orientated techniques.  In addition, Java natively supports the
    concept of <em>threads</em>, which allows more than one task to be
    performed at the same time.  A good understanding of Java, and especially
    object-orientated programming (OOP) and threading, will help
    you get the most out of Struts and this User Guide. </p>

    <p>For more about Java and threads, see </p>

    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/java/index.html"><strong>Learning the Java Language</strong></a> in the Java Tutorial</li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/essential/threads/index.html">
        <strong>Threads: Doing Two or More Tasks At Once</strong></a> in the Java Language
        Tutorial</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Even if you have worked with Java and OOP before, it can also help to be aware of the
    programming challenges specific to creating and using application frameworks. For more about application
    frameworks, see the classic white papers</p>

    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://www.laputan.org/drc/drc.html"><strong>Designing Reusable Classes</strong></a> by Ralph E. Johnson &amp; Brian Foote</li>
    <li><a href="http://www.cs.wustl.edu/~schmidt/CACM-frameworks.html"><strong>Object-Oriented Application Frameworks</strong></a>
    by Mohamed Fayad and Douglas C. Schmidt</li>
    </ul>

    <p>These papers can be especially helpful if you are fact-finding or reviewing server-side
    <a href="http://directory.google.com/Top/Computers/Programming/Languages/Java/Server-Side/Libraries_and_Frameworks/">frameworks</a>.
    </p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.5 JavaBeans" href="javabeans">

    <p>Like many Java applications, most of the Struts objects are designed as
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/">JavaBeans</a>. Following the JavaBean design patterns makes
    the Struts classes easier to use -- both by Java developers and by Java development tools. </p>

    <p>Although JavaBeans were first created for visual elements, these object design patterns have been found to
    be useful as the basis for any reusable component, like those used by the Struts framework.</p>

    <p>For more about JavaBeans, see:</p>

    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/docs/"><strong>The
        JavaBeans Component Architecture Documentation</strong></a> page at
        <code>java.sun.com</code>, including a link to download the
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/docs/spec.html">
        JavaBeans 1.01 Specification</a></li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/javabeans/index.html">
        <strong>The JavaBean Trail</strong></a> in the Java Tutorial</li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/JSPBeans.html">
        <strong>JavaBeans Components in JSP Pages</strong></a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial
        </li>
    </ul>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.5.1 Reflection and Introspection" href="reflection">

    <p>
    Reflection is the process of determining which member fields and methods are available on an object.
    Introspection is a specialized form of reflection used  by the JavaBean API.
    Using Introspection, we can determine which methods of a JavaBean are intended to be accessed by other objects.
    (The getters and the  setters, for example.)
    </p>

    <p>
    The Struts framework uses Introspection to convert HTTP parameters into JavaBean properties and to populate HTML fields from JavaBean properties.
    This technique makes it easy to "roundtrip" properties between HTML forms and JavaBeans.
    </p>

    <p>
    For more about Reflection and Introspection, see
    </p>

    <ul>
    <li>
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/reflect/">The Reflection Trail</a>
    </li>
    <li>
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/docs/spec.html">Chapter 8 of the JavaBeans API Specification</a>
    </li>
    </ul>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.5.2 Maps" href="Maps">

    <p>
    JavaBeans store data as properties and may act on that data through other methods.
    JavaBeans are flexible and powerful objects but are not the only object that programmers use to store data.
    Another popular object is the Map [<code>java.util.Map</code>].
    A Map is a simple collection of name and value pairs.
    Maps are often used "behind the scenes" as a flexible way to store dynamic data.
    </p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.5.3 DynaBeans" href="dynabeans">

    <p>
    DynaBeans combine the extensibility of JavaBeans with the flexibility of a Map.
    Defining even the simplest JavaBean requires defining a new class and coding a field and two methods for each property.
    The properties of a DynaBean can be configured via an XML descriptor.
    The virtual properties of a DynaBean can't be called by standard Java methods,
    but work well with components that rely on reflection and introspection.
    </p>

    <p>
    In a Struts application, you can use DynaBeans to describe your HTML forms.
    This strategy can avoid creating a formal JavaBean subclass to store a few simple properties.
    </p>

    <p>
    For more about DynaBeans, see
    </p>

    <ul>
    <li>
    The Commons BeanUtils
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/beanutils/api/org/apache/commons/beanutils/package-summary.html#package_description">
    Package Description</a> and <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/commons/beanutils/api/index.html">Javadocs</a>.
    </li>
     <li>
         <a href="https://formdef.dev.java.net/">Struts FormDef</a>
     </li>
    </ul>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.6 Properties Files and ResourceBundles" href="resources">

    <p>Java applications, including web applications, are often configured using
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.1/docs/api/java/util/Properties.html">Properties</a>
    files. Properties files are the basis for the
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.1/docs/api/java/util/ResourceBundle.html">ResourceBundles</a> that Struts uses to provide message resources
    to an application. </p>

    <p>For more about Properties files, see: </p>

    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/essential/attributes/properties.html">
    <strong>Using Properties to Manage Program Attributes</strong></a> in The Java Tutorial</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Java ResourceBundles use one or more Properties files to provide internationalized messages
    to users based their
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.1/docs/api/java/util/Locale.html">Locale</a>.
    Support for localizing an application was built into Struts from the ground-up.</p>

    <p>For more about localization and ResourceBundles, see </p>

    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/docs/books/tutorial/i18n/resbundle/concept.html"><strong>About the ResourceBundle Class</strong></a>
    in the Java Tutorial</li>
    </ul>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.7 Java Servlets" href="servlets">
    <p>
    Since Java is an object-orientated language, the
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/">Java Servlet</a>
    platform strives to cast HTTP into an object-orientated form.
    This strategy makes it easier for Java developers to concentrate on what they need their application to do --
    rather than the mechanics of HTTP.
    </p>

    <p>
    HTTP provides a standard mechanism for extending servers called the Common Gateway Interface, or CGI.
    The server can pass a request to a CGI-aware program, and the program will pass back a response.
    Likewise, a Java-aware server can pass a request to a servlet container.
    The container can fulfill the request or it can pass the request back to the HTTP server.
    The container decides whether it can handle the request by checking its list of servlets.
    If there is a servlet registered for the request, the container passes the request to the servlet.
    </p>

    <p>
    When a request comes in, the container checks to see if there is a servlet registered for that request.
    If there is a match,
    the request is given to the servlet.
    If not, the request is returned to the HTTP server.
    </p>

    <p>
    It's the container's job to manages the servlet lifecycle.
    The container creates the servlets, invokes the servlets, and ultimately disposes the servlets.
    </p>

    <p>
    A servlet is generally a subclass of <code>javax.servlet.http.HttpServlet</code>.
    A servlet must implement four methods, which are invoked by the container as needed:
    </p>

      <ul>
      <li><strong>public void init(ServletConfig config)</strong> - Called by the
          servlet container when the servlet instance is first created, and
          before any request is processed.</li>
      <li><strong>public void doGet(HttpServletRequest request,
          HttpServletResponse response)</strong> - Called to process a
          specific request received using the HTTP <code>GET</code> protocol,
          which generates a corresponding dynamic response.</li>
      <li><strong>public void doPost(HttpServletRequest request,
          HttpServletResponse response)</strong> - Called to process a
          specific request received using the HTTP <code>POST</code> protocol,
          which generates a corresponding dynamic response.</li>
      <li><strong>public void destroy()</strong> - Called by the servlet
          container when it takes this servlet instance out of service,
          such as when a web application is being undeployed or when the
          entire container is being shut down.</li>
      </ul>

    <p>
    Struts provides a ready-to-use servlet for your application [<code>org.apache.struts.action.ActionServlet</code>].
    As a Struts developer, you can then just write objects that the Struts ActionServlet calls when needed.
    But it is still helpful to understand the basics of what servlets are,
    and the role they play in a Java web application.
    </p>

    <p>
    For more about Java Servlets, see:
    </p>

    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/"><strong>The
        Java Servlet Technology</strong></a> page at
        <code>java.sun.com</code></li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/download.html"><strong>The
        Servlet 2.2 and 2.3 Specifications</strong></a> download page at
        <code>java.sun.com</code></li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/Servlets.html">
        <strong>Java Servlet Technology</strong></a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial.</li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/WebApp.html">
        <strong>Web Applications</strong></a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial.</li>
    </ul>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.7.1 Servlets and threads" href="threads">

    <p>
    To boost performance, the container can multi-thread servlets.
    Only one instance of a particular servlet is created,
    and each request for that servlet passes through the same object.
    This strategy helps the container make the best use of available resources.
    The tradeoff is that the servlet's <code>doGet()</code> and <code>doPost()</code> methods must be programmed in a <em>thread-safe</em> manner.
    </p>

    <p>
    For more about servlets and thread-safety, see:
    </p>

    <ul>
    <li>
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/Servlets5.html#64386">Controlling Concurrent Access to Shared Resources</a> in Java Web Services Tutorial.
    </li>
    </ul>

    </subsection>

      <subsection name="0.7.2 Servlet Context" href="context">

      <p>The <em>ServletContext</em> interface [<code>javax.servlet.ServletContext</code>] defines a servlet's view of
      the web application within which the servlet is running.  It is
      accessible in a servlet via the <code>getServletConfig()</code> method,
      and in a JSP page as the <code>application</code> implicit variable.
      Servlet contexts provide several APIs that are very useful in building
      Struts based web applications:</p>
      <ul>
      <li><em>Access To Web Application Resources</em> - A servlet can
          access static resource files within the web application using the
          <code>getResource()</code> and <code>getResourceAsStream()</code>
          methods.</li>
      <li><em>Servlet Context Attributes</em> - The context makes available
          a storage place for Java objects, identified by string-valued keys.
          These attributes are global to the entire web application, and may
          be accessed by a servlet using the <code>getAttribute()</code>,
          <code>getAttributeNames()</code>, <code>removeAttribute()</code>, and
          <code>setAttribute()</code> methods.  From a JSP page, servlet
          context attributes are also known as "application scope beans".
          </li>
      </ul>

    <p>
    For more about the servlet context, see:
    </p>

    <ul>
    <li>
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/Servlets10.html#64724">Accessing the Web Context</a> in Java Web Services Tutorial.
    </li>
    </ul>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="0.7.3 Servlet Request" href="request">

      <p>Each request processed by a servlet is represented by a Java
      interface, normally a <code>HttpServletRequest</code>
      [<code>javax.servlet.http.HttpServletRequest</code>].
      The request interface provides an object-oriented mechanism to access
      all of the information that was included in the underlying HTTP request,
      including:</p>
      <ul>
      <li><em>Cookies</em> - The set of cookies included with this request
          are available via the <code>getCookies()</code> method.</li>
      <li><em>Headers</em> - HTTP headers that were included with
          the request are accessible by name. You can enumerate the names
          of all included headers.</li>
      <li><em>Parameters</em> - Request parameters, including those from
          the query string portion of the URL and from the embedded content
          of the request (POST only) are available by name.</li>
      <li><em>Request Characteristics</em> - Many other characteristics
          of the incoming HTTP request, such as the method used (normally
          GET or POST) the protocol scheme used ("http" or "https"), and
          similar values.</li>
      <li><em>Request URI Information</em> - The original request URI
          being processed is available via <code>getRequestURI()</code>.
          In addition, the constituent parts into which the servlet container
          parses the request URI (contextPath, servletPath, and pathInfo) are
          available separately.</li>
      <li><em>User Information</em> - If you are using
          <a href="#security">Container Managed Security</a>, you can ask for
          the username of the authenticated user, retrieve a
          <code>Principal</code> object representing the current user, and
          whether the current user is authorized for a specified role.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>In addition, servlet requests support <em>request attributes</em>
      (from JSP, these are "request scope beans"), analogous to the servlet
      context attributes described above. Request attributes are often used
      to communicate state information from a business logic class that
      generates it to a view component (such as a JSP page) that will use
      the information to produce the corresponding response.</p>

      <p>The servlet container guarantees that a particular request will
      be processed by a servlet on a single thread. Therefore, you do not
      generally have to worry about the thread safety of your access to
      request properties and attributes.</p>

    <p>
    For more about the servlet request, see:
    </p>

    <ul>
    <li>
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/Servlets7.html#64433">Getting Information from Requests</a> in Java Web Services Tutorial.
    </li>
    </ul>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="0.7.4 Servlet Response" href="response">

      <p>The primary purpose of a servlet is to process an incoming
      <a href="#request">Servlet Request</a> [<code>javax.servlet.http.HttpServletRequest</code>]
      and convert it into a
      corresponding response. This is performed by calling appropriate
      methods on the servlet response [<code>javax.servlet.http.HttpServletResponse</code>]
      interface. Available methods let you:</p>
      <ul>
      <li><em>Set Headers</em> - You can set HTTP headers that will be
          included in the response.  The most important header is the
          <code>Content-Type</code> header, which tells your client what
          kind of information is included in the body of this response.
          This is typically set to <code>text/html</code> for an HTML page,
          or <code>text/xml</code> for an XML document.</li>
      <li><em>Set Cookies</em> - You can add cookies to the current
          response.</li>
      <li><em>Send Error Responses</em> - You can send an HTTP error status
          (instead of a usual page of content) using
          <code>sendError()</code>.</li>
      <li><em>Redirect To Another Resource</em> - You can use the
          <code>sendRedirect()</code> method to redirect the client to
          some other URL that you specify.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>An important principle in using the servlet response APIs is that
      any methods you call to manipulate headers or cookies
      <strong>MUST</strong> be performed before the first buffer-full of
      content has been flushed to the client. The reason for this restriction
      is that such information is transmitted at the beginning of the HTTP
      response, so trying things like adding a header after the headers have
      already been sent will not be effective.</p>

      <p>
      When you are using presentation pages in a Model 2 application,
      you will not generally use the servlet response APIs directly.
      In the case of JavaServerPages, the JSP page compiler
      in your servlet container will convert your page into a servlet.
      The JSP servlet renders the response, interspersing dynamic
      information where you have interposed JSP custom tags.
      </p>

      <p>
      Other presentation systems, like Velocity Tools for Struts,
      may delegate rendering the response to a specialized servlet,
      but the same pattern holds true.
      You create a template,
      and the dynamic response is generated automatically from the template.
      </p>

    <p>
    For more about the servlet response, see:
    </p>

    <ul>
    <li>
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/Servlets7.html#64531">Constructing Responses</a> in Java Web Services Tutorial.
    </li>
    </ul>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="0.7.5 Filtering" href="filter">

      <p>If you are using a servlet container based on version
      <strong>2.3</strong> or later of the Servlet Specification (such as
      Tomcat 4.x), you can take advantage of the new Filter APIs
      [<code>javax.servlet.Filter</code>] that
      let you compose a set of components that will process a request or
      response. Filters are aggregated into a chain in which each filter
      has a chance to process the request and response before and after
      it is processed by subsequent filters (and the servlet that is ultimately
      called).</p>

      <p>The Struts 1.0, 1.1, and 1.2 versions require only version 2.2 or later
      of the Servlet Specification to be implemented by your servlet container,
      so those versions of Struts do not use Filters. Beginning with the Struts
      1.3 version, a container that supports version 2.3 or later of the Servlet
      Specification is required, and it is possible that Struts itself might use
      Filters in the future.</p>
      
      <p>
      For more about filters, see:
      </p>

    <ul>
    <li>
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/Servlets8.html#64572">Filtering Requests and Responses</a>
    </li>
    </ul>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="0.7.6 Sessions" href="session">

      <p>One of the key characteristics of HTTP is that it is
      <em>stateless</em>. In other words, there is nothing built in to
      HTTP that identifies a subsequent request from the same user as being
      related to a previous request from that user. This makes building an
      application that wants to engage in a conversation with the user over
      several requests to be somewhat difficult.</p>

      <p>To alleviate this difficulty, the servlet API provides a programmatic
      concept called a <em>session</em>, represented as an object that
      implements the <code>javax.servlet.http.HttpSession</code> interface.
      The servlet container will use one of two techniques (cookies or
      URL rewriting) to ensure that the next request from the same user will
      include the <em>session id</em> for this session, so that state
      information saved in the session can be associated with multiple
      requests. This state information is stored in <em>session
      attributes</em> (in JSP, they are known as "session scope beans").</p>

      <p>To avoid occupying resources forever when a user fails to complete
      an interaction, sessions have a configurable <em>timeout interval</em>.
      If the time gap between two requests exceeds this interval, the session
      will be timed out, and all session attributes removed. You define a
      default session timeout in your web application deployment descriptor,
      and you can dynamically change it for a particular session by calling
      the <code>setMaxInactiveInterval()</code> method.</p>

      <p>Unlike requests, you need to be concerned about thread safety on
      your session attributes (the methods these beans provide, not the
      <code>getAttribute()</code> and <code>setAttribute()</code> methods
      of the session itself). It is surprisingly easy for there to be
      multiple simultaneous requests from the same user, which will therefore
      access the same session.</p>

      <p>Another important consideration is that session attributes occupy
      memory in your server <em>in between</em> requests. This can have
      an impact on the number of simultaneous users that your application can
      support. If your application requirements include very large numbers of
      simultaneous users, you will likely want to minimize your use of
      session attributes, in an effort to control the overall amount of memory
      required to support your application.</p>

      <p>
      For more about sessions, see:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/Servlets11.html#64744">Maintaining Client State</a> in Java Web Services Tutorial
        </li>
        <li>
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/servlet/2.1/api/javax.servlet.http.HttpSession.html"><code>javax.servlet.http.HttpSession</code></a>
        </li>
      </ul>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="0.7.7 Dispatching Requests" href="dispatch">

      <p>
      The Java Servlet specification extends the HTTP request/response cycle by allowing the request to be dispatched,
      or forwarded, between resources.
      Struts uses this feature to pass a request through specialized components,
      each handling one aspect of the response.
      In the normal course, a request may pass through a controller object, a model object,
      and finally to a view object as part of a single request/response cycle.
      </p>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="0.7.8 Web Applications" href="webapp">

      <p>
      Just as a HTTP server can be used to host several distinct web sites,
      a servlet container can be used to host more than one web application.
      The Java servlet platform provides a well-defined mechanism for organizing and deploying web applications.
      Each application runs in its own namespace so that they can be developed and deployed separately.
      A web application can be assembled into a Web Application Archive, or WAR file.
      The single WAR can be uploaded to the server and automatically deployed.
      </p>

    <p>
    For more about web applications, see:
    </p>
    <ul>
    <li>
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/WebApp.html#76431">Web Applications</a> in Java Web Services Tutorial
    </li>
    </ul>

      </subsection>

      <subsection name="0.7.9 Web application deployment descriptor (web.xml)" href="events">

      <p>
      Most aspects of an application's lifecycle are configured through an XML document called the Web application deployment descriptor.
      The schema of the descriptor, or web.xml, is given by the Java servlet specification.
      </p>

      <p>
      For more about the web.xml and application lifecycle events, see:
      </p>
      <ul>
      <li>
      <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/WebApp2.html#64550">Web Application Life Cycle</a> in Java Web Services Tutorial
      </li>
      </ul>

      </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.7.10 Security" href="security">

    <p>
    One detail that can be configured in the Web application deployment descriptor is container-managed security.
    Declarative security can be used to protect requests for URIs that match given patterns.
    Pragmatic security can be used to fine-tune security make authorization decisions based on the time of day,
    the parameters of a call, or the internal state of a Web component.
    It can also be used to restrict authentication based on information in a database.
    </p>

      <p>For more information about container-managed security, see:</p>
      <ul>
      <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.2/tutorial/doc/index.html">
          Web Application Security (Chapter 24)</a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial
      </li>
      </ul>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.8 JavaServer Pages, JSP Tag Libraries, and Java Server Faces" href="jsp">
    <p><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/product.html">JavaServer Pages</a> (JSPs) are
    "inside-out servlets" that make it easier to create and maintain dynamic web pages. Instead
    of putting what you want to write to the HTTP response inside of a Java <code>print</code>
    statement, everything in a JavaServer Page is written to the response, <strong>except</strong> what is
    placed within special Java statements.</p>

    <p>With <strong>JavaServer Pages</strong> you can start by writing the page in standard HTML and then add the
    dynamic features using statements in the Java language or by using
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/taglibraries.html">JSP tags</a>.
    The Struts distribution includes several JSP tags that make it easy to access the framework's
    features from a JavaServer Page.</p>

    <p>For more about JavaServerPages and Custom JSP Tag Libraries see  </p>

    <ul>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/"><strong>The
        JavaServer Pages Technology</strong></a> page at
        <code>java.sun.com</code></li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/download.html"><strong>The
        JSP 1.1 and 1.2 Specifications</strong></a> download page at
        <code>java.sun.com</code></li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/JSPIntro.html"><strong>JavaServer Pages Technology</strong></a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial</li>
    <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/JSPTags.html"><strong>Custom Tags in JSP Pages</strong></a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Many times, JSP tags work hand-in-hand with JavaBeans. The application sends a JavaBean to
    the JSP, and the JSP tag uses the bean to customize the page for the instant user. For more, see
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/JSPBeans.html">JavaBeans Components in JSP Pages</a>
    in the Java Web Services Tutorial.</p>

    <p>Struts also works well with the
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp/jstl"><strong>JavaServer Pages Standard Tag Library</strong></a>
    (JSTL) and taglibs from other sources, like
    <a href="http://jsptags.com/">JSP Tags</a>,
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/taglibs/index.html">Jakarta Taglibs</a>,
    <a href="http://struts.application-servers.com">Struts Layout</a>, and
    <a href="http://http://displaytag.sourceforge.net/">Display Tags</a>.
    </p>

    <p>
        One of the subprojects available for Struts Classic is <a href="http://struts.apache.org/struts-el/index.html">Struts-EL</a>.
        This taglib is specifically designed to work well with JSTL.
        In particular, it uses the same "expression language" engine for evaluating tag attribute values as JSTL.
        This is in contrast to the original Struts tag library, which can only use "rtexprvalue"s (runtime scriptlet
        expressions) for dynamic attribute values.
    </p>

    <p>There are also toolkits available that make Struts easy to use with
    <a href="http://stxx.sourceforge.net/">XSLT</a> and
    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/tools/index.html">Velocity Templates</a>.
    </p>

        <p>
            The newest star on the Java horizon is  <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/javaserverfaces/">JavaServer Faces technology</a>.
            JSF simplifies building user interfaces for JavaServer applications, both for the web and for the desktop.
            To keep pace, Struts is offering a new framework to go with this new technology, called
            <a href="http://struts.apache.org/struts-shale/index.html">Struts Shale</a>.
            For teams looking for a smoother transition to JSF, we offer Struts-Faces taglib,
            which lets you use JSF components with your existing Actions.
        </p>
        <p>
            For an open source implementation of JSF, visit our sibling project
           .
        </p>

        <p>For more about JSTL and JavaServer Faces see  </p>

       <ul>
           <li>
               <a href="http://today.java.net/pub/a/today/2003/10/07/jstl1.html">Practical JSTL, Part 1</a>
               by Sue Spielman
           </li>
           <li>
               <a href="http://www.jsfcentral.com"><strong>JSF Central</strong></a> - JavaServer Faces resources.
            </li>
           <li>
               <a href="http://www.jamesholmes.com/JavaServerFaces/"><strong>JavaServer Faces Resources</strong></a>
            - James Holmes dot Com.
           </li>
           <li> <a href="http://myfaces.apache.org">Apache MyFaces</a> - An open source implementation of
               the JSF specification.
           </li>
       </ul>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.9 Extensible Markup Language (XML)" href="xml">

    <p>The features provided by the Struts framework relies on a number of objects that are
    usually deployed using a configuration file written in
    <a href="http://www.w3.org/XML/">Extensible Markup Language</a>. XML is also used to
    configure Java web applications; so, this is yet another familiar approach.
    </p>

    <p>For more about XML configuration files and Java web applications, see</p>

    <ul>
    <li>
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/WebApp4.html#64678">Configuring Web
        Applications</a> in the Java Web Services Tutorial</li>
    </ul>

    <p>
        For more about how XML is used with Java applications generally, see
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/JAXPIntro.html">Java API for XML Processing</a>
        in the Java Web Services Tutorial.
        While the framework makes good use of this API internally, it is not something most Struts developers would use
        when writing their own applications.
    </p>

    </subsection>

        <subsection name="0.9.1 Descriptors" href="descriptors">

        <p>
        When Java applications use XML configuration files,
        the elements are most often used as <em>descriptors</em>.
        The application does not use the XML elements directly.
        The elements are used to create and configure (or deploy) Java objects.
        </p>

        <p>
        The Java Servlet platform uses an XML configuration file to deploy servlets (among other things).
        Likewise, Struts uses an XML configuration file to deploy objects used by the framework.
        </p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.10 Other layers" href="layers">

    <p>
      Struts provides the control layer for a web application. Developers can use this layer with
      other standard technologies to provide the data access and presentation layers. Some
      popular Data access technologies include:
    </p>

        <ul>
            <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/ejb/index.html">Enterprise Java Beans</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://www.hibernate.org/">Hibernate</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://ibatis.apache.org">iBATIS</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jdbc/index.html">JDBC</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://db.apache.org/ojb/">Object Relational Bridge</a></li>
        </ul>

    <p>
      Presentation layer technologies include:
    </p>

        <ul>
        <li><a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsp">JavaServer Pages</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/index.html">Velocity Templates</a></li>
        <li><a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt">XSL Transformations </a></li>
        </ul>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="0.11 JAAS" href="jaas">

    <p>
        While Struts can work with any approach to user authentication and authorization, Struts 1.1 and later offers
        direct support for the standard Java Authentication and Authorization Service (JAAS).
        You can now specify security roles on an action-by-action basis.
    </p>

    <p>For more about JAAS, see the <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/jaas/index-14.html">Javasoft product page</a>
    and the <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/doc/WebAppSecurity.html">
    Web Application Security</a> chapter of the
    <a href="http://java.sun.com/webservices/docs/1.0/tutorial/index.html">Java Web Services Tutorial</a>.</p>

    <p>
        A popular extension for handling security in a Java web application, including a Struts application,
        is <a href="http://securityfilter.sourceforge.net/">SecurityFilter</a>.
    </p>


</subsection>

<subsection>
    <p class="right">
    Next: <a href="introduction.html">Introduction</a>
    </p>
</subsection>

</section>
</body>
</document>
