<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="release-notes.html">
  <properties>
    <title>Struts Release Notes (since 1.2.7)</title>
  </properties>
 <body>
 <section name="6.1 Release Notes - Version 1.3.0-dev">
 <a name="release_notes"/>
      <subsection name="Introduction">
          <p>
              This section contains release notes for changes that have taken
              place to Struts Classic since
              <a href="release-notes-1.2.7.html">Version 1.2.7</a>.
              To keep up-to-date on all changes to Struts, subscribe to the
              (commits at struts.apache.org) list.
          </p>
          <p>
              <b>Notes on upgrading</b> are maintained in the
              <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/struts/StrutsUpgrade">Wiki Upgrade pages</a>.
              The wiki is a community maintained resource - please feel free to add your
              input so that everyone can benefit from the collective experience.
          </p>
          <p>
             For the version requirements of each library, see the 
             <a href="installation.html">Installation chapter</a>.
          </p>
 
      </subsection>

      <a name="Highlight"/>
      <subsection name="Highlights of Changes">
          <p>
              The purpose of this section is to highlight the new features since the
              Version 1.2.7 release.
              For more detail, see the Project Info reports for each subproject,
              which include a complete changelog and list of external dependencies.
          </p>

          <h3>People</h3>

          <p>
              On the <a href="../volunteers.html">volunteer</a> front, two new committers,
              <i>Wendy Smoak</i> and <i>Gary VanMatre</i>, accepted invitations
              to join us.
          </p>

          <h3>Struts Classic</h3>

          <p>
              Since Struts 1.2.7, we have subdivided Struts into several subprojects,
              each with its own release cycle.
              The codebases that were part of Struts 1.2.7 will start with version 1.3.0,
              but, thereafter, will increment independently of each other.
          </p>

          <p>
              Since many teams will use more than one Struts subproject,
              we are bundling several of the subprojects in a single distribution
              called "Struts Classic".
              The seven subprojects included in the Struts Classic 1.3.0 distribution
              are: Applications, Core, EL, Plugins, Site, Taglibs, and Tiles.
          </p>

          <p>
              The Struts website and Struts Classic distribution are being built with Maven.
              But, of course, you can continue to build your own projects any way you like!)
          </p>

          <h3>Struts Applications</h3>

          <p>...</p>

          <h3>Struts Core</h3>

          <p>...</p>

          <h3>Struts EL</h3>

          <p>...</p>

          <h3>Struts Plugins</h3>

          <p>...</p>

          <h3>Struts Site</h3>

          <p>...</p>

          <h3>Struts Taglibs</h3>

          <p>...</p>

          <h3>Struts Tiles</h3>

          <p>...</p>

      </subsection>

     <subsection>
       <p class="right">Next:
       <a href="installation.html">Installation</a></p>
     </subsection>
 </section>
</body>
</document>
