<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document url="syste.html">
<!--
    WARNING: This file is automatically generated from a jsdoc processor that
    turns javadoc-type comments of Javascript and special Java files into an xml file, which is
    then processed by an xsl file to create this document. Do not modify this
    file, but rather either modify the comments or xsl file.
  -->
<properties>
<title>Core Flow Methods </title>
</properties>
<body>
<section href="summary" name="Core Flow Methods ">
<p> <p> These methods are available to every flow script automatically to simplify interactions with the flow engine. They can be overridden as necessary for advanced customizations like intercepting every function call to perform some common logic like security checks. </p> <p>The only method that should be called from an application's flow scripts  is <a href="#fn_forwardAndWait">forwardAndWait()</a> as the others are mainly just used by the framework.  They are exposed to allow the user to easily customize functionality. </p> </p>
<dl/>
<table width="100%">
<tr>
<th colspan="2">Function Summary</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="5%">
<code>Continuation </code>
</td>
<td>
<strong>
<code>
<a href="#fn_forwardAndWait">forwardAndWait(name, atts, allowedRemoteFuncs)</a>
</code>
</strong>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="5%">
<code>void </code>
</td>
<td>
<strong>
<code>
<a href="#fn_handleContinuation">handleContinuation(kont)</a>
</code>
</strong>
</td>
</tr>
</table>
</section>
<section name="Functions">
<section href="fn_forwardAndWait" name="forwardAndWait">
<pre>Continuation  forwardAndWait(name, atts, allowedRemoteFuncs)</pre>
<p> Forwards to a page and creates a continuation. Contains special support for client FlowCall's (calling flow functions through asynchrous javascript calls from the client).  The forward name will be used to find the appropriate Struts ActionForward to return from the Action. </p>
<dl>
<dt>
<strong>Parameters:</strong>
</dt>
<dd>
<code>name</code> - 
                The Struts forward name to call </dd>
<dd>
<code>atts</code> - 
                Map of business objects to place in the request scope </dd>
<dd>
<code>allowedRemoteFuncs</code> - 
                A list of remote function names that are allowed        to be called from asynchronously from the client.  An empty array        allows any function call, a null or not specified array allows none. </dd>
</dl>
<dl>
<dt>
<strong>Returns: </strong>
</dt>
<dd>The continuation created used in the call </dd>
</dl>
</section>
<section href="fn_handleContinuation" name="handleContinuation">
<pre>void  handleContinuation(kont)</pre>
<p> This function is called by Struts Flow to restart a previously saved continuation passed as argument.  Override this method to have control over how continuations are instantiated. </p>
<dl>
<dt>
<strong>Parameters:</strong>
</dt>
<dd>
<code>kont</code> - 
                The continuation to reload </dd>
</dl>
<dl/>
</section>
</section>
</body>
</document>
