<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="release-notes-1.0.html">

  <properties>
    <title>Struts Release Notes (Version 1.0)</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Introduction" href="Introduction">

    <p>This document contains the release notes for
    <strong>Version 1.0</strong> of the Struts Framework,
    and covers changes that have taken place since
    <a href="release-notes-1.0-b3.html">Version 1.0-beta-3</a>
    was released.  The following sections cover
    <a href="#New">New Features</a> and <a href="#Changes">Changes</a>
    to Struts.</p>

  </section>


  <section name="What's Included?" href="Included">

    <p>The binary distribution of this release includes the following
    files relevant to Struts 1.0:</p>
    <ul>
    <li><code>INSTALL</code> - Brief installation instructions.  See
        the <code>Struts Documentation Application</code>, or online at
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/</a>
        for more information.</li>
    <li><code>LICENSE</code> - The Apache Software Foundation license that
        defines the terms under which you can use Struts (and other software
        licensed by Apache).</li>
    <li><code>README</code> - A brief introduction to Struts.</li>
    <li><code>lib/</code> - Directory containing files you will need in
        your own applications.  The individual files of interest are:
        <ul>
        <li><code>struts.jar</code> - JAR file that contains the compiled
            Java classes for both version 0.5 and 1.0 of Struts.  You must
            place this file in the <code>/WEB-INF/lib</code> directory of
            your web application.</li>
        <li><code>struts-xxxxx.tld</code> - The tag library descriptor files
            for the Struts 1.0 tag libraries (bean, html, logic, and
            template).  You must place these files in the <code>/WEB-INF</code>
            directory of your web application, and reference them with
            appropriate <code>&lt;taglib&gt;</code> directives in your
            web.xml file.  <strong>NOTE</strong> - The struts-form.tld
            file is deprecated; you should use the struts-html.tld file
            instead.</li>
        <li><code>jdbc2_0-stdext.jar</code> - The JDBC 2.0 Optional Package
            API classes (package <code>javax.sql</code>).  You will need to
            include this file in the <code>/WEB-INF/lib</code> directory
            of your application, if it is not already made visible to web
            applications by your servlet container.</li>
        <li><code>struts-config_1_0.dtd</code> - The document type descriptor
            (DTD) for the Struts configuration file (which is typically named
            <code>/WEB-INF/struts-config.xml</code>.  Your configuration file
            will be validated against an internal copy of this DTD -- this
            copy is available for reference purposes only.</li>
        <li><code>web-app_2_2.dtd</code> - The document type descriptor (DTD)
            for web.xml files conforming to the Servlet 2.2 specification.
            This copy is for reference purposes only.</li>
        <li><code>web-app_2_3.dtd</code> - The document type descriptor (DTD)
            for web.xml files conforming to the Servlet 2.3 specification.
            This copy is for reference purposes only.</li>
        </ul></li>
    <li><code>webapps/</code> - Web Application Archive (WAR) files for the
        web applications that are included with Struts.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>For backwards compatibility only, the binary distribution also
    includes the following files that conform to the Struts 0.5 milestone
    release APIs.  Usage of these files and APIs is deprecated, and they
    will be removed from releases after Struts 1.0:</p>
    <ul>
    <li><code>lib/</code> - Directory containing files you will need in
        your own applications.  The individual files of interest are:
        <ul>
        <li><code>struts.jar</code> - JAR file that contains the compiled
            Java classes for both version 0.5 and 1.0 of Struts.  You must
            place this file in the <code>/WEB-INF/lib</code> directory of
            your web application.</li>
        <li><code>struts.tld</code> - The tag library descriptor file for
            the 0.5 version of the Struts tags.  You must place this file
            in the <code>/WEB-INF</code> directory of your web application,
            and reference it with appropriate <code>&lt;taglib&gt;</code>
            directives in your web.xml file.</li>
        </ul></li>
    </ul>

  </section>


  <section name="What's New?" href="New">

    <p><strong>DEPRECATIONS</strong> - The entire custom tag library
    that is documented in <code>struts.tld</code> has been deprecated.
    These tags correspond to the Struts 0.5 functionality that is also
    deprecated, and have been replaced (and considerably enhanced) in
    the various individual tag libraries.</p>

    <p><strong>DEPRECATIONS</strong> - The entire custom tag library
    that is documented in <code>struts-form.tld</code> has been deprecated
    because this library has been renamed <code>struts-html.tld</code>
    instead.</p>

    <p><strong>DEPRECATIONS</strong> - Several classes in the
    <code>org.apache.struts.util</code> package have been marked as
    deprecated in their entirety, because they will be replaced by
    versions from the Jakarta Commons project once those packages are
    released.  These deprecated classes will <strong>not</strong> be
    removed until a release after Struts 1.1.  In general, the only
    change required inside user code using these classes will be to
    update the <code>import</code> statement.  The following classes
    are involved:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>ArrayStack</li>
    <li>BeanUtils</li>
    <li>ConvertUtils</li>
    <li>FastArrayList</li>
    <li>FastHashMap</li>
    <li>FastTreeMap</li>
    <li>GenericConnection</li>
    <li>GenericDataSource</li>
    <li>PropertyUtils</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following new features have been added to the basic controller
    framework (package <code>org.apache.struts.action</code>):</p>

    <p>The following new features have been added to the utility classes
    (package <code>org.apache.struts.util</code>):</p>


    <p>The following new features have been added to the
    <em>struts-html</em> custom tag library (package
    <code>org.apache.struts.taglib.html</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>The <code>&lt;html:link&gt;</code> tag now supports the optional
        <code>title</code> attribute, that causes some browsers to display
        alternate text when the mouse is hovered over a hyperlink.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following new features have been added to the
    <em>struts-logic</em> custom tag library (package
    <code>org.apache.struts.taglib.logic</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>The <code>&lt;logic:iterate&gt;</code> tag now supports a new
        attribute, <code>indexId</code>.  This attribute names a page scope
        attribute (and corresponding scripting variable) that will be
        exposed in the nested body of the iteration, which will contain
        the current loop index as a java.lang.Integer.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following new features have been added to the
    <em>struts-template</em> custom tag library (package
    <code>org.apache.struts.taglib.template</code>):</p>


    <p>The following new features have been added to the Struts Documentation
    application (and corresponding contents on the Struts web site):</p>

  </section>


  <section name="Changes and Bug Fixes" href="Changes">

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes have occurred in the configuration
    files related to Struts:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>The documentation about configuring a data source element in the
        <code>struts-config.xml</code> file has been updated to emphasize
        the use of <code>&lt;set-property&gt;</code> elements nested inside
        the <code>&lt;data-source&gt;</code> element.  No further additional
        attributes will be added to the <code>&lt;data-source&gt;</code>
        element in the DTD to support custom properties of particular
        data source implementations.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes have occurred in the basic
    controller framework (package <code>org.apache.struts.action</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>Several issues introduced with the internal wrapping of multipart
        requests have been fixed.</li>
    <li>The instance variables in the <code>ActionForm</code> base class
        are now transient, so that <code>ActionForm</code> instances can
        actually be serialized.  <strong>WARNING</strong> - If you deserialize
        such an <code>ActionForm</code> instance and attempt to use it within
        the Struts framework, be sure to call <code>setServlet()</code> (and
        <code>setMultipartRequestHander()</code> if appropriate) first.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes have occurred in the file upload
    package (package <code>org.apache.struts.upload</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>Fixed a bug that could cause corruption in the uploaded file,
        by converting sequences of \r\n\n into \r\n\r\n.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes have occurred in the utilities
    (package <code>org.apache.struts.util</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>Corrected a cut-and-paste typo that caused NullPointerException
        on attempts to use the new <code>pingQuery</code> property that
        was added in Struts 1.0-b3.</li>
    <li>Fix operation ordering so that <code>RequestUtils.lookup()</code>
        will throw a JspException when the specified bean is missing, in
        accordance with its JavaDoc documentation.</li>
    <li>Digester calls to <code>Rule.body()</code> methods will now trim
        leading and trailing whitespace first, consistent with the behavior
        of other body processing performed within the rules.</li>
    <li>Correct the calculation of an absolute URL from a context-relative
        path in <code>RequestUtils.absoluteURL()</code>.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes have occurred in the
    <em>struts-bean</em> custom tag library (package
    <code>org.apache.struts.taglib.bean</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>The <code>&lt;bean:include&gt;</code> tag will now pass a session
        identifier on to the included request (assuming that it is part of
        the same web application), even if the current request is maintaining
        session identity with cookies.  Previously, this only worked if you
        were using URL rewriting.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes have occurred in the
    <em>struts-html</em> custom tag library (package
    <code>org.apache.struts.taglib.html</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>For all tags where Struts generates attributes that are allowed to
        be minimized in the HTML specification (i.e. checked, disabled,
        multiple, readonly, and selected), generate attribute values equal
        to the attribute name, as required by HTML 4.01, section 3.3.4.
        For example, generate <code>checked="checked"</code> instead of
        <code>checked="true"</code> for the "checked" attribute.</li>
    <li>Correctly generate a <code>&lt;a name="my name"&gt;&lt;&gt;</code>
        element when the <code>linkName</code> attribute is used on the
        <code>&lt;html:link&gt;</code> tag.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes have occurred in the
    <em>struts-logic</em> custom tag library (package
    <code>org.apache.struts.taglib.logic</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>Update the processing performed by the
        <code>&lt;logic:present&gt;</code> and
        <code>&lt;logic:notPresent&gt;</code> tags to reflect the changed
        behavior of <code>RequestUtils.lookup()</code>.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes to the Struts Documentation
    application (and corresponding contents on the Struts web site) have
    occurred:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>Links to subscribe and unsubscribe from the STRUTS-DEV and
        STRUTS-USER mailing lists have been added to the home page.</li>
    <li>Miscellaneous corrections to typos and hyperlinks.</li>
    <li>Cleaned up problems in the stylesheets used to create documentation
        pages that formerly emitted <code>&lt;project&gt;</code> tags in the
        generated HTML, and generated incorrect references to link colors in
        the navigation bar.</li>
    <li>Added a "Who We Are" page to the documentation.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes to the Struts Example Application
    have occurred:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>The <code>name</code> and <code>page</code> attributes of the
        <code>&lt;app:checkLogon&gt;</code> tag now accept runtime
        expressions.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes to the Struts Template Example
    Application have occurred:</p>

  </section>


  </body>

</document>
