<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="release-notes-1.0.2.html">

  <properties>
    <title>Struts Release Notes (Version 1.0.2)</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Introduction" href="Introduction">

    <p>This document contains the release notes for
    <strong>Version 1.0.2</strong> of the Struts Framework,
    and covers changes that have taken place since
    <a href="release-notes-1.0.1.html">Version 1.0.1</a>
    was released.  The following sections cover
    <a href="#New">New Features</a> and <a href="#Changes">Changes</a>
    to Struts.</p>

    <p>This version covers bug-fixes only; no new functionality.</p>

  </section>


  <section name="What's Included?" href="Included">

    <p>The binary distribution of this release includes the following
    files relevant to Struts 1.0.2:</p>
    <ul>
    <li><code>INSTALL</code> - Brief installation instructions.  See
        the <code>Struts Documentation Application</code>, or online at
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/">http://jakarta.apache.org/struts/</a>
        for more information.</li>
    <li><code>LICENSE</code> - The Apache Software Foundation license that
        defines the terms under which you can use Struts (and other software
        licensed by Apache).</li>
    <li><code>README</code> - A brief introduction to Struts.</li>
    <li><code>lib/</code> - Directory containing files you will need in
        your own applications.  The individual files of interest are:
        <ul>
        <li><code>struts.jar</code> - JAR file that contains the compiled
            Java classes for version 1.0.2 of Struts.  You must
            place this file in the <code>/WEB-INF/lib</code> directory of
            your web application.</li>
        <li><code>struts-xxxxx.tld</code> - The tag library descriptor files
            for the Struts 1.0.2 tag libraries (bean, html, logic, and
            template).  You must place these files in the <code>/WEB-INF</code>
            directory of your web application, and reference them with
            appropriate <code>&lt;taglib&gt;</code> directives in your
            web.xml file.</li>
        <li><code>jdbc2_0-stdext.jar</code> - The JDBC 2.0 Optional Package
            API classes (package <code>javax.sql</code>).  You will need to
            include this file in the <code>/WEB-INF/lib</code> directory
            of your application, if it is not already made visible to web
            applications by your servlet container.</li>
        <li><code>struts-config_1_0.dtd</code> - The document type descriptor
            (DTD) for the Struts configuration file (which is typically named
            <code>/WEB-INF/struts-config.xml</code>.  Your configuration file
            will be validated against an internal copy of this DTD -- this
            copy is available for reference purposes only.</li>
        <li><code>web-app_2_2.dtd</code> - The document type descriptor (DTD)
            for web.xml files conforming to the Servlet 2.2 specification.
            This copy is for reference purposes only.</li>
        <li><code>web-app_2_3.dtd</code> - The document type descriptor (DTD)
            for web.xml files conforming to the Servlet 2.3 specification.
            This copy is for reference purposes only.</li>
        </ul>
        </li>
        <li><code>webapps/</code> - Web Application Archive (WAR) files for the
            web applications that are included with Struts.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>The struts 0.5 milestone API release is no longer supported,
       and will be removed as of Struts 1.1.</p>

  </section>


  <section name="What's New?" href="New">

    <p>No new features have been added in this release.</p>

  </section>


  <section name="Changes and Bug Fixes" href="Changes">

    <p>The following changes and bug fixes have occurred in the basic
    controller framework (package <code>org.apache.struts.action</code>):</p>
    <ul>
    <li>The <code>ActionForm.getMultipartRequestHandler()</code> method is now
        public rather than protected, to restore compatibility with the Tiles
        extension.</li>
    </ul>

  </section>


  </body>

</document>
