<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./acquiring.xml">

<!--
// ======================================================================== 78
-->

<properties>
    <title>Acquiring - The Apache Struts Web Application Framework</title>
</properties>

<body>

    <section name="Acquiring Struts" href="Acquiring">

    <p>
    Struts is available in a binary distribution, a source distribution, and a
    library distribution, which is a minimal binary distribution that includes
    only what you need to build your own applications with Struts.
    </p>
    <p>
    You may choose to download a production release, a milestone release, or a
    development build. All downloads are available to the general public at
    no charge and are distributed under the
    <a href="http://apache.org/licenses/">Apache Software License</a>.
    </p>
    <p>
    <strong>In addition to a Struts distribution,</strong> you will need to
    ensure that you have downloaded and installed all of the
    <a href="userGuide/installation.html#Prerequisites">prerequisite</a>
    software. Then, follow the appropriate instructions to
    <a href="userGuide/installation.html#Installing">
    install and use a Struts binary distribution</a> in your web application
    or for
    <a href="userGuide/installation.html#Building">
    building Struts from the source distribution</a>.
    </p>

</section>

<section name="Releases and Milestone Builds" href="ReleasesAndMilestones">
    <p>
    Releases and milestone builds of Struts are available from the main
    Struts distribution site, or from mirror sites.
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <strong>General Availability (GA) Releases</strong>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="http://struts.apache.org/download.cgi">
              Struts 1.2.7
            </a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>
        <strong>Older Releases</strong> are available from the 
        <ul>
          <li>
            <a href="http://archive.apache.org/dist/struts/">
              Archive Site
            </a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
</section>

<section name="Development Builds" href="DevelopmentBuilds">

    <p>
    The latest <em>development build</em> of Struts is available 
    <a href="http://svn.apache.org/dist/struts/">here</a>
    in binary, source and library distributions.
    </p>

    <p>
    Development builds are being reviewed for quality by the Struts community.
    When a build is judged "ready for prime time", it is promoted to "General
    Availability" status and may be made the "Best Available" release. A build
    that isn't quite there may be promoted to "Beta" status.
    </p>

</section>

<section name="Nightly Builds" href="NightlyBuilds">

    <p>
    For developers who are helping to develop Struts, or who just want "the
    latest bits", the latest development version is made available each morning.
    Use at your own risk!
    </p>

    <ul>

    <li>
        Nightly Builds of Struts Core, Taglib, Tiles, EL, Apps, and Plugins are 
        available here: 
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/builds/struts/maven/">Built by Maven</a>.
    </li>
    <li>
        Nightly Builds of some sub-projects, such as Shale, Struts Faces, 
        and Standalone Tiles (currently in the Sandbox) are available here:
        <a href="http://svn.apache.org/builds/struts/nightly/">Built by Ant</a>
    </li>

    </ul>

    <p>
    Be sure to check the <a href="userGuide/release-notes.html">
    Release Notes</a> for the nightly builds so you know what you are getting!
    </p>

</section>

<section name="Source Code" href="SourceCode">

    <p>
    Access to the source repository for Struts is available through both
    <a href="http://svn.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/struts/core/trunk/?root=Apache-SVN">web browser</a>
    and
    <a href="http://www.apache.org/dev/version-control.html">
    Subversion client</a> interfaces.</p>
    
    <p>
    To download the trunk (HEAD revision) of all struts projects, a convenience
    directory has been added, named current.  The current directory uses a 
    Subversion feature called externals which stores properties on the directory.
    With those properties Subversion has all the information it needs to download
    all the struts subprojects together automatically.
    </p>
    <p>There are some caveats to remember.  Since all the subdirectories are 
    still really different slices from the repository, relative paths won't 
    always work as expected, for example.  See the 
    <a href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/en/1.1/ch07s04.html">Externals 
    Definitions</a> section of the 
    <a href="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">Subversion Book</a> for details.
    </p>

    <p>To take advantage of this shortcut, use the following URL:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/current</li>
    </ul>

    
    <p>To check out individual sub-projects from the Subversion
    repository, you will need to specify one of the following URLs:
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/apps/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/bsf/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/core/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/el/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/faces/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/flow/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/sandbox/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/shale/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/taglib/trunk</li>
      <li>http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/tiles/trunk</li>
    </ul>
    <p>
    <strong>Warning:</strong> If you try to take a shortcut, and check out
    everything under 'struts', be aware that you will get not just the most
    recent code ('trunk'), but a copy of every tag and branch ever created
    for Struts. This will quite possibly fill up your entire disk!
    </p>

    <p>
    If you are building Struts from source, be sure to refer to the
    <a href="userGuide/installation.html">Installation page</a> in the
    User Guide for prerequisites. There are several JARs from the Jakarta
    Commons project that are required to build Struts.
    </p>

    <p>
    If you are interested in the Tag Library Descriptor (TLD) files, these
    files are generated as part of the build process. The source files from
    which they are generated are the struts-*.xml files found in the
    <a href="http://svn.apache.org/repos/asf/struts/core/trunk/doc/userGuide/">
    /doc/userGuide</a> folder of the main repository.
    </p>

</section>

<section>
    <p class="right">
    Next: <a href="using.html">Using Struts</a>
    </p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
