<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
Copyright 1999-2005 The Apache Software Foundation
Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<!--
// ======================================================================== 78
-->
<document>

<properties>
    <title>Welcome</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Struts @ ApacheCon">

    <p>        
     <a href="http://apachecon.com/2005/US"><img align="right" src="http://apache.org/images/ac2005us_white_184x80.jpg"/></a>
     Join us in San Diego CA at ApacheCon US 2005, December 11-14, for two presentations featuring Struts, 
     along with several other sessions involving Struts, as well as two special tutorial sessions on Saturday December 10.     
    </p>
    
    <p>
     <b>TU20: Struts 2006: An Embarrassment of Riches</b> 
    </p>
    
    <p>    
     [Tuesday at 4:30p with Don Brown and Ted Husted] 
     Apache Struts is a hotbed of activity. Struts Classic 1.3, Struts Shale, Struts Ti, Struts OverDrive. 
     Why so many frameworks? How are they different? Why are they all called Struts? 
     Which is the best choice for my next project? 
     In this session, we step back and look at Struts through a wide-angle lens.    
    </p>
    
    <p>
     <b>TU26: Shale: The Next Struts??</b>
    </p>
     
    <p>
     [Tuesday at 5:30p with Craig McClanahan] 
     Come and get an early look at the next generation of web application frameworks. 
     One that is based on the recenty standardized JavaServer Faces APIs, 
     and focuses on adding value, rather than redundantly implementing features that JSF already 
     provides. Shale will run on any compliant JSF implementation, including the one being developed by 
     the Apache MyFaces project. It also includes many features that Struts users appreciate, such as 
     supporting client side validation and the Tiles framework.
    </p>
    
    <p>
     <b>T06: Building Adaptable Meta-Components for Struts, Tapestry, MyFaces, etc.</b>
    </p>
    
    <p>
     [Saturday at 10a with Johnathan Lehr] 
     Learn how to design, build, and use powerful, coarse-grained components using the Struts framework in 
     this intensive, hands-on tutorial. We'll integrate an available ListView component into an example 
     application and then learn how to build a TreeView component from scratch. The ListView component will 
     provide fully implemented pagination, sorting, filtering, selection management, styling, and drill-down 
     for arbitrary columns defined in an XML config file. The TreeView will allow recursive nesting, and will 
     support a config setting allowing it to switch between an AJAX update mode.  
    </p>
        
    <p>
     <b>T12: Struts on Steroids: Leveraging Bolt-On Components</b>
    </p>
    
    <p>
     [Saturday at 1p with Johnathan Lehr]     
     Learn how to design, build, and use powerful, coarse-grained components using the Struts framework in 
     this intensive, hands-on tutorial. We'll integrate an available ListView component into an example 
     application and then learn how to build a TreeView component from scratch. The ListView component will 
     provide fully implemented pagination, sorting, filtering, selection management, styling, and drill-down 
     for arbitrary columns defined in an XML config file. The TreeView will allow recursive nesting, and will 
     support a config setting allowing it to switch between an AJAX update mode, and an update mode relying on 
     the standard form.
    </p>
       
    <p>
     Other presentations involving Struts include:    
    </p>

    <ul>
     <li>T01: <b>How to Unit Test the User Interface of Web Applications</b> </li>
     <li>MO07: <b>Portals@Apache: Standards and the Portals Projects</b> </li>
     <li>MO22: <b>Roller: An Open Source Blogging Platform</b> </li>
    </ul>
    
    <p>
     A complete listing of scheduled sessions is available at the 
     <a href="http://apachecon.com/2005/US/html/sessions.html">ApacheCon US 2005 site</a>.
    </p> 
     
</section>

<section name="Welcome to Apache Struts!">
<a name="Welcome"/>
    <p>
        The goal of the Apache Struts project is to encourage application
        architectures based on the "Model 2" approach, a variation of the
        classic Model-View-Controller (MVC) design paradigm.
        Under Model 2,
        a servlet (or equivalent) manages business logic execution,
        and presentation logic resides mainly in server pages.
    </p>

    <p>
        The Apache Struts project encourages Model 2 designs in two ways.
        First, by providing open source frameworks and toolkits
        that help developers build applications for the web.
        Second, by providing friendly and honest mailing lists
        where both newcomers and veterans discuss how to use Struts software
        in their own Model 2 applications.
    </p>

    <p>
        Originally, the Apache Struts software was distributed
        as one monolithic bundle.
        Today, the Struts project is comprised of several subprojects.
        Each subproject has its own website, documentation, and release cycle,
        and may be downloaded separately.
        The six original Apache Struts subprojects --
        Core, Taglibs, Tiles, Extras, Applications, and EL --
        are also being bundled into a distribution known as "Struts Classic".
    </p>

    <p>
        Apache Struts is a volunteer project and
        all support for the framework is provided by unpaid volunteers.
        This documentation bundle and the mailing lists are the primary ways
        to learn how to use Struts.
        The next few pages are devoted to helping you understand
        what resources are available to you.
        Since Apache Struts is a volunteer project,
        and our resources are limited,
        it is important that we first help you help yourself.
    </p>

    <ul>
        <li>
            Struts is a project of the <a href="http://www.apache.org">
            The Apache Software Foundation</a>.
        </li>
        <li>
            The official Apache Struts home page is at
            <a href="http://struts.apache.org/"> http://struts.apache.org/</a>.
        </li>
    </ul>

</section>

<section>
   <p class="right">
    <strong>Next:</strong> <a href="announce.html">Announcements</a>
   </p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
