<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./index.xml">

<!--
// ======================================================================== 78
-->

<properties>
    <title>Apache Struts Project</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Welcome to Apache Struts!">
<a name="Welcome"/>
    <p>
        The goal of the Apache Struts project is to encourage application
        architectures based on the "Model 2" approach, a variation of the
        classic Model-View-Controller (MVC) design paradigm.
        Under Model 2,
        a servlet (or equivalent) manages business logic execution,
        and presentation logic resides mainly in server pages.
    </p>

    <p>
        The Apache Struts project encourages Model 2 designs in two ways.
        First, by providing open source frameworks and toolkits
        that help developers build applications for the web.
        Second, by providing friendly and honest mailing lists
        where both newcomers and veterans discuss how to use Struts software
        in their own Model 2 applications.
    </p>

    <p>
        Originally, the Apache Struts software was distributed
        as one monolithic bundle.
        Today, the Struts project is comprised of several subprojects.
        Each subproject has its own website, documentation, and release cycle,
        and may be downloaded separately.
        The six original Apache Struts subprojects --
        Core, Taglibs, Tiles, Extras, Applications, and EL --
        are also being bundled into a distribution known as "Struts Classic".
    </p>

    <p>
        Apache Struts is a volunteer project and
        all support for the framework is provided by unpaid volunteers.
        This documentation bundle and the mailing lists are the primary ways
        to learn how to use Struts.
        The next few pages are devoted to helping you understand
        what resources are available to you.
        Since Apache Struts is a volunteer project,
        and our resources are limited,
        it is important that we first help you help yourself.
    </p>

    <ul>
        <li>
            Struts is a project of the <a href="http://www.apache.org">
            The Apache Software Foundation</a>.
        </li>
        <li>
            The official Apache Struts home page is at
            <a href="http://struts.apache.org/"> http://struts.apache.org/</a>.
        </li>
    </ul>

</section>

<section>
   <p class="right">
   Next: <a href="volunteers.html">Who We Are</a>
   </p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
