<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
Copyright 1999-2005 The Apache Software Foundation
Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
You may obtain a copy of the License at

http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<!--
// ======================================================================== 78
-->
<document><properties>
<title>Kickstart FAQ</title>
</properties>
<body>
<a name="faq"/>
<section name="Kickstart FAQ">

<a name="contents"/>
<subsection name="Index">

<p>
Here are answers to the some of the usual Apache Struts getting-started questions. 
</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#shale">Why are you offering both Struts Shale and Struts Action Framework? Don't they compete for new development?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#2x">Is Shale likely to become Struts 2.x?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#shale-fork">Is Struts Shale a fork?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ti">What about Ti? What about WebWork?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ti2">Does Ti mean there will be three frameworks?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#overdrive">What about OverDrive or Struts Nexus?</a></li>    
    <li><a href="#classic">What's the difference between Struts Action Framework and Struts Classic</a></li>
  </ul>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="#struts">Why is it called Struts?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#license">How is Apache Struts licensed?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#usage">Can Apache Struts be used in a commercial application?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#credits">Do I have to credit Apache Struts on my own website?</a></li>
  </ul><ul>
    <li><a href="#requests">If a product doesn't do what I want, can I request that a feature be added?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#help">Where can I get help with Apache Struts?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#support">Is commercial support available for Apache Struts?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#providers">Are there ISPs that will host my Apache Struts application?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#ide">Is there a particularly good IDE to use with Struts Action Framework?</a></li>
  </ul><ul>
    <li><a href="#digest">Is there a digest for the Apache Struts User list?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#newsgroup">Is there a Apache Struts Newsgroup?</a></li>
    <li><a href="#mailbounce">Why didn't my posting show up on the user list?"</a></li>
    <li><a href="#unsubscribe">How do I unsubscribe from the mailing list?</a></li>
  </ul>

<p>
For other FAQs, see the documentation for each subproject.
</p>

</subsection>

<a name="shale"/>
<subsection name="Why are you offering both Struts Shale and Struts Action Framework? Don't they compete for new development?">
<p>We do offer Apache Struts developers a choice, but, hey, choice is good. :)</p>
<p>People who want to create and maintain Struts Action Framework are welcome to do so.</p>
<p>People who want to create and maintain Struts Shale are equally welcome.</p>
<p>As a volunteer organization, we are not constrained by the economics of competition. All we need are volunteers who are ready, willing, and able to do the work. So long as we have volunteers, we have work for them to do. :)</p>
<p>Right now, we have volunteers who want to leverage the new JavaServer Faces framework by using Struts Shale for new development. We also have volunteers who prefer to leverage their existing investment in Struts Action Framework. All are welcome.</p>
<p>For more about volunteering, visit our <a href="http://struts.apache.org/faqs/helping.html">how to help page</a>.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="fork"/>
<subsection name="Is Struts Shale a fork?">
<p>No. It's an entirely new product with its own architecture. Struts Shale is an MVC framework for web applications, like Struts Action Framework, but it's a fresh start. Struts Shale is the best choice for developers eager to leverage the latest technologies, like JavaServer Faces.</p>
<p>Both frameworks will have a home here so long as there are volunteers ready to contribute.</p>
<p>We encourage you to choose the framework that works best for you. (Even if it is not one of ours!)</p>
</subsection>

<a name="2x"/>
<subsection name="Is Shale likely to become Struts 2.x?">
<p>Struts Shale has its own identity and its own release cycle. Struts Action Framework is one subproject, and Struts Shale is another.</p>
<p>So, no, it is not likely that Struts Shale will become Struts Action Framework 2.x.</p>
<p>
There is another proposal on the table for a Struts Action Framework 2.x candidate ("Struts Ti"). 
But, it still only a proposal.
</p>
<p>In our opinion, the reasons to roll the major version number are when</p>
<ul>
    <li>a new codebase is created, or</li>
    <li>there is a break in backward compatability.</li>
</ul>
<p>Should either of these things happen, then, in that event, there would be a Struts Action Framework 2.x.</p>
<p>For example, right now, most of us are using Java 1.3 in production, so that is the platform that Struts Action Framework targets. But, if someone wanted to start a "Struts Tiger" codebase, using the new features of Java 1.5, something like that might be a candidate for Struts Action Framework 2.x.</p>
<p>But, so long as each Struts Action Framework release follows the deprecate/replace/remove strategy, and targets the mainstream platform, we will just keep rolling the minor version number. If this takes us to Struts 1.42 or Struts 1.2025, then so be it.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="ti"/>
<subsection name="What about Ti? What about WebWork?">
<p>
<a href="http://wiki.apache.org/struts/StrutsTi">Struts Ti</a> 
(short for Titanium) is a proposal for a Struts Action Framewok 2.x candidate. 
In late November 2005, the Ti proposal was amended to include a merger with 
<a href="http://www.opensymphony.com/webwork/">Open Symphony WebWork</a>. 
Under this plan, the next stable release of WebWork would be donated to Apache Struts, 
and the lead WebWork committers would join the Struts community. 
</p>
<p>
WebWork started as a <a href="http://incubator.apache.org/learn/rules-for-revolutionaries.html">Struts Revolution</a>. 
Over the years, it has evolved into a superb action-based framework that retains many Struts 1.x paradigms. 
</p>
<p>
People who have worked with both Struts 1.x and WebWork 2.x tend to agree that it is a logical candidate for Struts Action Framework 2.x.
If you look the Struts Action 1.x roadmap and the WebWork 2.x feature set, 
you'll see that WebWork has already does most of what we wanted Struts Action to do. 
If we finished the roadmap ourselves, Struts Action would end up as a WebWork workalike. 
Rather than reinvent the wheel, 
Ti has become a proposal to put the WebWork wheel back on the Struts axle.
</p>
<p>
Of course, many of us have significant Struts Action 1.x applications in production. 
Being able to migrate both applications and developer skill sets is a telling point of the proposal.
Both a migration layer and migration documentation are under active development.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="ti2" />
<subsection name="Does Ti mean there will be three frameworks?">
<p>
Probably not. 
Like many projects, we start by giving proposed subprojects a codename. 
Sun's "Tiger" and Microsoft's "Vista" are two examples. 
"Ti" is a codename like "Tiger" and "Vista. 
If Struts Ti is accepted as Struts Action Framework 2.x, the codename would fall into disuse. 
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="overdrive" />
<subsection name="What about OverDrive or Struts Nexus?">
<p>
<a href="http://wiki.apache.org/struts/StrutsOverDrive">OverDrive</a> 
is a working proposal to use a set of case-study applications 
to drive the design and creation of a business layer framework. 
The codename for the business layer framework under development is "Nexus". 
Like Action and Shale, the Nexus internals are based on the Chain of Responsibility pattern.
</p>
<p>
OverDrive and Nexus do not complete with frameworks like Action and Shale. 
Nexus begins where these frameworks end. 
Nexus is the "rest of the stack". 
</p>
<p>
The codebase underlying the proposal is being coded in C#, but a version for Java is expected in due course. 
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="action"/>
<subsection name="What's the difference between Struts Action Framework and Struts Classic?">
<p>For the Struts Action Framework 1.3.x series, we subdivided the monolithic Struts 1.2.x distribution into several discrete subprojects. Struts Classic is a codename for the work we needed to do to create and release the new subprojects. </p>
<p>For a time, we considered bundling those seven products together and calling the bundle "Struts Classic". Instead, we are bundling Struts Action Framework and any compatible projects into a distribution called "Struts Action Framework Library". This bundle includes the original "seven dwarfs" and new subprojects, like Struts Scripting.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="struts"/>
<subsection name="Why is it called Struts?">
<p>It's a reference to struts in the architectural sense, a reminder of the nearly invisible pieces that hold up buildings, houses, and bridges.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="license"/>
<subsection name="How is Apache Struts licensed?">
<p>All Apache Struts products are copyrighted software available under the <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses">Apache License</a>, a &quot;free-to-use, business-friendly license&quot;.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="usage"/>
<subsection name="Can Apache Struts be used in a commercial product?">
<p>Yes. The only requirements you must meet are those listed in the <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses">Apache License</a>.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="credits"/>
<subsection name="Do I have to credit Apache Struts on my own website?">
<p>You need to credit Apache Struts if you <strong>redistribute your own framework</strong> based on our products
for other people to use. (See the <a href="http://www.apache.org/LICENSE">Apache License</a> for details.)
But you do <strong>not</strong> need to credit Apache Struts just because your web application utilizes one of our products.
It's the same situation as using the Apache HTTPD server or Tomcat. Not required if its just running your web site.
Required if you've used the source code to create your own server that you are redistributing to other people.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="requests"/>
<subsection name="If a product doesn't do what I want, can I request that a feature be added?">
<p>
First, it's important to remember that Apache Struts is an all-volunteer project.
We don't charge anyone anything to use Apache Struts products.
Committers and other developers work on Apache Struts products because they need to use it with their own applications.
If others can use it too, that's "icing on the cake".
If you <a href="../helping.html">submit a patch</a> for a feature that a Committer finds useful, then that Committer may choose to volunteer his or her time to apply the patch.
If you just submit an idea without a patch, it is much less likely to be added (since first someone else has to volunteer their time to write the patch).
</p>
<p>
We are grateful for any patches, and we welcome new ideas, but the best way to see that something gets added to the framework is to do as much of the work as you can, rather than rely on the "kindness of strangers". Worst case, you can apply the patch to your copy of Struts and still use the feature in your own application. (Which is what open source is ~really~ all about.)
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="help"/>
<subsection name="Where can I get help with Apache Struts?">
<p>Struts Action Framework comes complete with a
<a href="../userGuide/index.html">Users Guide</a> to
introduce people to the framework and its underlying technologies. Various components
also have their own in-depth Developers Guide, to cover more advanced topics. Comprehensive
<a href="../api/index.html">Javadocs</a> are included
along with the <strong>full source code</strong>.
</p>
<p>
The
<a href="http://struts.apache.org/mail.html">Struts user mailing list</a> is also
very active, and welcomes posts from new users. Before posting a new question, be
sure to consult the
<a href="http://struts.apache.org/mail.html#Archives">
<strong>MAILING LIST ARCHIVE</strong></a> and the very excellent
<a href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">
How To Ask Questions The Smart Way</a> by Eric Raymond. Please do be sure
to <a href="http://expita.com/nomime.html">turn off HTML</a> in your
email client before posting.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="support"/>
<subsection name="Is commercial support available?">
<p>The Apache Software Foundation does not provide commercial support for any of our software products, including Apache Struts products. 
However, third parties may offer different degrees of support. </p>
</subsection>

<a name="providers"/>
<subsection name="Are there ISPs that will host my Struts application?">
<p>For a listing of some Java and Struts Action Framework ISPs, visit the <a href="http://struts.sf.net/community/index.html">Struts Community Resources</a> area on SourceForge.</p>
</subsection>

<a name="ide"/>
<subsection name="Is there a particularly good IDE to use with Struts Action Framework">
<p>
Struts should work well with any development environment that you would like to use, as well as with any programmers editor.
The members of the Struts development team each use their own tools such as
<a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/emacs.html">Emacs</a>,
<a href="http://www.intellij.com/idea/">IDEA</a>,
<a href="http://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse</a>,
and <a href="http://www.netbeans.org/">NetBeans</a>.
</p>
<p>
See the <a href="../faqs/index.html">Howto Guides</a> for more about configuring IDEs to work with Struts.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="digest"/>
<subsection name="Is there a digest for the User list?">
<p>
Yes. <a href="mailto:user-digest-subscribe@struts.apache.org">send a blank message</a> to &lt; <a href="mailto:user-digest-subscribe@struts.apache.org">user-digest-subscribe@struts.apache.org</a>&gt;.
</p>
<p>
If you are subscribed to the digest, you can also post to the list.
Just be sure to send your post to the
<a href="mailto:user@struts.apache.org">user list</a> rather than trying to reply to the digest.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="newsgroup"/>
<subsection name="Is there an Apache Struts newsgroup?">
<p>
Not a usenet group, but the Struts User list can be accessed with your
favorite newsgroup reader from the
<a href="http://news.gmane.org/">GMane News Site</a>.  Subscribe to groups
<code>gmane.comp.jakarta.struts.devel</code> for the developer list, or
<code>gmane.comp.jakarta.struts.user</code> for the user list.
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="mailbounce"/>
<subsection name="Why didn't my posting show up on the user list?">
<p>
You must be subscribed to the <a href="mailto:user-subscribe@struts.apache.org">user list</a>
or <a href="mailto:user-digest-subscribe@struts.apache.org">user digest</a> before posting
(or use the <a href="http://news.gmane.org">GMane Newsgroups</a> instead).
</p>
</subsection>

<a name="unsubscribe"/>
<subsection name="How do I unsubscribe from the mailing list?">
<p>
<strong>From the email account used to subscribe to the list,</strong> <a href="mailto:user-unsubscribe@struts.apache.org">send a blank message</a> to &lt; <a href="mailto:user-unsubscribe@struts.apache.org">user-unsubscribe@struts.apache.org</a>&gt;.
</p>
<p>
If you are receiving the digest, you must send a blank email to
&lt;<a href="mailto:user-digest-unsubscribe@struts.apache.org">user-unsubscribe@struts.apache.org</a>&gt;
instead.
</p>
</subsection>

</section>

    <section>
       <p class="right">
	<strong>Next:</strong> <a href="helping.html">How to Help FAQ</a>
       </p>
    </section>

</body></document>
