<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="./using.xml">

<!--
// ======================================================================== 78
-->

<properties>
    <title>Using - The Apache Struts Web Application Framework</title>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Using Struts">

    <p>
    In the normal course of using an application framework like Struts,
    you may wish to
    </p>

    <ul>

    <li>
        <a href="#Bugs">report a bug or feature request</a>,
    </li>

    <li>
        <a href="#Patches">contribute a patch</a>,
    </li>

    <li>
        <a href="#Lists">join the mailing lists</a>,
    </li>

    <li>
        <a href="#Questions">post a question</a>,
    </li>

    <li>
        or otherwise <a href="#Involved">become involved</a> with the Struts 
        Community.
    </li>

    </ul>

    </section>

    <section name="Reporting Bugs and Feature Requests" href="Bugs">

    <p>
    Tracking of bug reports and enhancement requests for Struts is handled
    through the <a href="http://issues.apache.org/bugzilla"> Apache Bug 
    Database</a>. 
    Please select <strong>Struts</strong> from the product list, along with 
    the details of which component of Struts you feel this report
    relates to, and details of your operating environment. 
    You will automatically be notified by email as the status of your bug or
    enhancement report changes. 
    Please be sure to read
    <a href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/bugs.html">How to 
    Report Bugs Effectively</a> before posting.
    </p>

</section>

<section name="Contributing Patches to Code or Documentation" href="Patches">

    <p>
    You can upload a proposed <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/source.html#Patches">
    patch</a> to either the code or documentation by creating a feature request in
    <a href="#Bugs">Bugzilla</a>. 
    <strong>After creating the ticket</strong>, you can go back and upload a file 
    containing your patch.
    </p>

    <p>
    The documentation is maintained in the <code>doc</code> folder of the
    repository in a XML format.
    In the Nightly Build, there is a "compile.website" target in the 
    <code>build.xml</code> file, which renders the XML into the HTML we post 
    to the Website. 
    If you would like to help with the documentation, it is important to 
    provide patches and new pages in the XML source. 
    Otherwise, some other volunteer will have to do this for you, and it may 
    never get done. 
    (Sad but true.) 
    If you are submitting new material, it is important to decide exactly 
    where you would put this in relation to the rest of the documentation. 
    Someone has to figure that out before it can be added, and that someone 
    might as well be you.
    </p>

    <p>
        If you have comments on existing material, you can make comments via the Struts Wiki. Just follow the
        "Comments?" link on any page.
        If you are making a substantial contribution, such as a new HOW-TO, please consider submitting a document in
        the XML format we use.
        This will make it easier to add your contribution to the official documentation so that it becomes part of the
        WAR distributed with Struts.
    </p>

    <p>
    For more, see the <a href="./faqs/helping.html">How to Help FAQ</a>.
    </p>

</section>

<section name="Joining the Mailing Lists" href="Lists">

    <p>
    Before joining any Apache mailing list, please be sure to read the
    <a href="mail.html#Guidelines">Mailing List Guidelines</a>.
    If you have read and understood these guidelines, you are welcome to
    <a href="mail.html#Subscribing">join the Struts mailing lists</a>.
    </p>
    
</section>

<section name="Posting a Question to a Mailing List" href="Questions">

    <p>
    Before posting a new question, be sure to consult one of the
    <a href="mail.html#Archives">
    <strong>Mailing List Archives</strong></a> and the very excellent
    <a href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">
    How To Ask Questions The Smart Way</a> by Eric Raymond.
    </p>

    <p>
    Please do be sure to <a href="http://expita.com/nomime.html">turn off  HTML</a> in your email client before posting.
    </p>

    </section>

    <section name="Getting Involved" href="Involved">

    <p>
        All work on Struts (and other Apache projects) is provided on an all-volunteer basis.
        For more about what you can do, see the Apache Jakarta
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/getinvolved.html">Getting Involved Overview</a> and the Struts
        <a href="./faqs/helping.html">How to Help FAQ</a>.
    </p>

</section>

<section>
    <p class="right">
    <strong>Next:</strong> <a href="volunteers.html">Who We Are</a>
    </p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
