<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="index.html">

  <properties>
    <title>Struts Flow</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Struts Flow" href="overview">
      <p>
Struts Flow is a port of <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org">Cocoon's</a> <a
href="http://cocoon.apache.org/2.1/userdocs/flow/index.html">Control Flow</a> to Struts to allow complex workflow, like
multi-form wizards, to be easily implemented using continuations-capable JavaScript. It provides the ability to describe
the order of Web pages that have to be sent to the client, at any given point in time in an application. The flow
scripts fulfill the role of Struts Actions, however, they can be used along side traditional Java-based Struts Actions.

        </p>
        <p>This is an example of a Struts Flow server-side script which logs the user on to an application:
        <pre>
function login() {
  userManager = struts.applicationScope["userManager"];
  error = "";
  while (struts.sessionScope["curUser"] == null) {
    forwardAndWait("loginForm", {"error" : error});
    user = struts.param["user"];
    passwd = struts.param["passwd"];
    if (userManager.login(user, passwd)) {
      struts.sessionScope["curUser"] = user;
    } else {
      error = "Invalid login, please try again";
    }
  }
}  
        </pre>
        The <code>forwardAndWait()</code> method sends an HTML page to the user and waits for a response. When the form
        is submitted, Struts Flow restores the variable values and restarts the script where it left off. There are more
        detailed examples in the <a href="#examples">Examples</a> section.
        </p>
        <p>
        Since continuations are best implemented in Javascript, Struts Flow also focuses on making Javascript
        easier to use and better integrated into the Java environment borrowing several ideas from <a 
        href="http://groovy.codehaus.org">Groovy</a>.  First, information in Collections classes
        can be accessed using Javascript array (<code>foo[1]</code>) and object (<code>foo["bar"]</code>) notations.
        Also, Struts Flow uses <a href="http://www.json.org">JSON</a> to allow client-side Javascript running
        in a browser to call server-side Javascript flow functions.  <a href="http://www.trimpath.com/project/wiki/JavaScriptTemplates">Javascript Templates</a>
        can be used on the server and client side with Struts Flow to support a 100% Javascript view layer.
        Finally, core Java API classes like <code>java.io.File</code> have additonal methods and properties
        added to them.  For example, to process each line of a text file, you can use the following closure:
        </p>
<pre>
  file = new java.io.File("foo.txt");
  file.eachLine(
    function(line) {
      print(line);
    }
  );
</pre>
        <p>
        While the initial target of the extracted Control Flow is Struts, the Flow code and Javascript extensions
        are reusable from other 
        non-Struts environments.  This means Control Flow could be used to drive non-Struts JSP applications, portlets, or even complex web services.
        </p>
    </section>  
      <section name="Features" href="features">
            <ul>
              <li>Easily script complex workflows</li>
              <li>Full access to Struts features</li>
              <li>Can exist side-by-side regular Struts actions</li>
              <li>Ability to run in non-Struts environments (uses Jakarta's Commons-Chain)</li>
              <li>Enhanced Java API methods and Collections integration</li>
              <li>Remote RPC support (termed Ajax but with JSON instead of XML) for calling flow methods from the client</li>
              <li>Includes Wizard library to help easily create complex wizards</li> 
              <li>Includes <a href="http://www.trimpath.com/project/wiki/JavaScriptTemplates">Javascript Templates</a> library to replace JSP for a 100% Javascript view layer.</li> 
              <li>Includes number guessing, remote rpc, Javascript Templates, and wizard examples</li> 
            </ul>
      </section>
      <section name="Documentation and Examples" href="examples">
        <p>
          The quickest way to understand how Struts Flow works is to take a look at the examples below, and even to
          download and run them yourself. Once you have your "hello world" application running, use the "Built-in
          Resources" section on the left to learn what methods and variables Struts Flow makes available to every
          script. Finally, Struts Flow enhances the standard Java API by adding methods and properties to many classes
          to keep your Struts Flow scripts short and to the point. A list of the extensions is also on the left under
          the heading"Java Enhancements".
        </p>
             <p>The following examples show how Struts Flow can be used:
             </p>
            <ul>
                <li><a href="guess-example.html">Number Guess Game Example</a> - A simple number guessing game</li>
                <li><a href="remote-example.html">Number Guess Game Example - Remote Edition</a> - The above game but with a remote call from the client Javascript to let the user "cheat"</li>
                <li><a href="templates-example.html">Number Guess Game Example - Templates Edition</a> - The above example, but rendering all HTML on both the server and client side using <a
        href="http://www.trimpath.com/project/wiki/JavaScriptTemplates">Javascript Templates</a>.</li>
                <li><a href="wizard-example.html">Wizard Example</a> - Shows a simple wizard framework built on top of Struts Flow that handles back and forward navigation automatically.</li>
            </ul>
          <p>
            For more documentation about the general concept of flow and continuations, the <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org">Apache Cocoon</a> <a href="http://cocoon.apache.org/2.1/userdocs/flow/index.html">Control Flow</a> pages might be useful as the core of Struts Flow was originally extracted from Cocoon.
          </p>
       </section>   
      <section name="What's New" href="new">
        <section name="0.5 - Unreleased">
            <ul>
              <li>Added better Collections support within Javascript</li>
              <li>Upgraded Rhino library to 1.6 which features native continuations support</li>
              <li>Added framework for adding methods and properties to core Java API classes</li>
              <li>Added JSON support</li>
              <li>Added client Javascript library and server-side support for calling flow functions from the brower</li>
              <li>Added Javascript Templates library for generating HTML content on the server and client side</li>
              <li>Moved project to Apache Struts</li>
              <li>Added new remote number guessing game example to demonstrate remote Javascript flow calls</li>
              <li>Added new templates number guessing game example to demonstrate a 100% Javascript application</li>
              <li>Added new documentation generated from the Java and Javascript source files</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="0.2 - September 10, 2004">
            <ul>
              <li>Added wizard library to make wizard creation easy</li>
              <li>Added wizard example</li>
              <li>Updated and improved documentation</li>
              <li>Fixed a few bugs</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="0.1 - June 3, 2004">
            <ul>
              <li>Hooks into Struts' logging</li>
              <li>Added continuation expiration system</li>
              <li>Added support for JavaScript debugger</li>
              <li>Improved Struts integration</li>
              <li>Added full JavaDocs</li>
              <li>Added many more configuration options</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="Initial Import - May 12, 2004">
            <ul>
              <li>Example working</li>
              <li>Struts integration functioning</li>
              <li>Needs better Struts form integration</li>
              <li>Needs to hook into Struts' logging</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
     </section>   
      <section name="Requirements" href="requirements">
          <p>
            Struts-specific features of Struts Flow requires Struts 1.1 or greater.
          </p>
      </section>
 </body>
</document>
